<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cosmeticks or, the beautifying part of physick. By which all deformities of nature in men and women are corrected, age renewed, youth prolonged, and the least impediment, from a hair to a tooth, fairly amended. With the most absolute physical rarities for all ages. Being familiar remedies, for which every one may be his own apothecary. / All extracted out of that eminent physician John Jeams Wecker, never yet extant in the English tongue before, but was promised to the world by Mr. Nic. Culpeper.</title>
            <author>Wecker, Johann Jacob, 1528-1586.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1660</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 79 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96154</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W1235</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E2140_3</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R208368</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99867325</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99867325</idno>
            <idno type="VID">119632</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96154)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 119632)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 243:E2140[3])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cosmeticks or, the beautifying part of physick. By which all deformities of nature in men and women are corrected, age renewed, youth prolonged, and the least impediment, from a hair to a tooth, fairly amended. With the most absolute physical rarities for all ages. Being familiar remedies, for which every one may be his own apothecary. / All extracted out of that eminent physician John Jeams Wecker, never yet extant in the English tongue before, but was promised to the world by Mr. Nic. Culpeper.</title>
                  <author>Wecker, Johann Jacob, 1528-1586.</author>
                  <author>Culpeper, Nicholas, 1616-1654, attributed name.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 140, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Tho. Johnson, at the White Cock in Rood-lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1660.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Aug:".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cosmetics --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Medicine, Popular --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Beauty, Personal --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-10</date>
            <label>Anne Simpson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>COSMETICK OR, <hi>The Beautifying Part</hi> OF PHYSICK.</p>
            <p>By which all Deformities of Nature in Men and Women are corrected, Age renewed, Youth prolonged, and the leaſt Impediment, from a Hair to a Tooth, fairly amended.</p>
            <p>With the moſt abſolute Phyſical Rarities for all Ages.</p>
            <p>Being familiar Remedies, for which every one may be his own Apothecary.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>All extracted out of that eminent Phyſician</hi> John Jeams Wecker, <hi>never yet extant in the Engliſh Tongue before, but was promiſed to the world by</hi> Mr. Nic. Culpeper.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>Tho. Johnſon,</hi> at the <hi>White Cock</hi> in <hi>Rood-lane.</hi> 1660.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:2"/>
            <head>To all truly vertuous LADIES.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Ladies,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THe ſuſpition and jea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſie that every man has of himſelf, when he is to publiſh any thing of no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velty to the world, makes a man always willing at that time to ſpeak ſomething for himſelf, and in the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>half
<pb facs="tcp:119632:3"/>of what he writes. As for the preſumption of this Addreſs, I am confident it will be eaſily excuſed in me, doing no more than what all the world does, while they endeavour to ſerve, with the utmoſt of their diligence, that Sex, for whoſe reading this little VVork was chiefly inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. For theſe <hi>Secrets of Nature</hi> by which Nature hath taught us how to beautifie, and make her ſelf
<pb facs="tcp:119632:3"/>more comely, coming to my hands, I could not chuſe but diſperſe them for the Benefit of thoſe to whom I owe ſo great a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect. To ſpeak of the things themſelves, they are ſuch, as the moſt diligent Searchers into Natures Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crets, have delved out of her moſt hidden and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cealed Bowels, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed by them with ſo much Art, and Experience, that for the certainty of
<pb facs="tcp:119632:4"/>their Operation, they ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs, I may boldly ſay, what ever has been to this purpoſe yet made. Nor let any think it irreligion, to make <hi>Age</hi> endure comely and graceful, or to cover thoſe deformities by which the decay of Time renders a perſon not only unhand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom, but deſpicable? why ſhould a woman looſe one of the chiefeſt Ornaments of her whole frame, a long Train of diſheveled Hair,
<pb facs="tcp:119632:4"/>if that can be reſtored by Art, which has been loſt by the malice of ſome Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eaſe? VVhy ſhould not the height of Cleanlineſs be as much in commenda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as the height of Slut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſhneſs is diſcommended? Briefly therefore we ſhall ſay once more of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, That there is nothing therein contained, but what the poor, as far as they are concerned (for all Phyſick it ſelf is not for their purſe)
<pb facs="tcp:119632:5"/>may uſe with profit, and the Rich both to their profit and pleaſure. Therefore <hi>Ladies,</hi> buy theſe few Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceipts, and make uſe of 'um, and if they fail, then never believe me another time; which diſpleaſure of yours I would not willingly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cur, out of my zeal always to appear,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>LADIES,</salute> 
               <signed> 
                  <hi>Your moſt faithful and devoted Servant,</hi> L. D.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="index">
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:5"/>
            <head>THE INDEX.</head>
            <list>
               <head>B</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>Balls againſt the Plague and Peſtilence.</hi> Page 137.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Burns.</hi> Page 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Biles and botches.</hi> Page 92, 93</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beaurifie the face.</hi> Page 107, 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Breaſts made ſmall.</hi> Page 116, 117</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made leſs.</hi> Page 118</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to hinder their growth.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to harden them.</hi> Page 119, 120</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to make the ſmooth.</hi> Page 117</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>for thoſe that hang down.</hi> Page 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Black and blewneſs of the Eyes and Eyelids.</hi> Page 84</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Beard cauſed.</hi> Page 69, 70</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baldneſs.</hi> Page 65, 66, 68</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Brighten the face.</hi> Page 21, 24</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Black the face.</hi> Page 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Bunches in the face.</hi> Page 37, 93</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119632:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Body fatted.</hi> Page 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baths for the body.</hi> Page 40, 41</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Baths for the Cholerick.</hi> Page 40</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>for the skin.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ſweet for great men.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>C</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>COunteſs of</hi> Arnsburgs <hi>Perfume.</hi> Page 138</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colour hair and beard black.</hi> Page 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cold.</hi> Page 59</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Cleopatra's Ointment.</hi> Page 64, 87, 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clefts of the lips.</hi> Page 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Colouring for the face.</hi> Page 107, 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clefts of the hands</hi> &amp;c. Page 113, 114</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Clefts of the nibbels.</hi> Page 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Candels to Perfume.</hi> Page 135</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>D</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>DArkneſs of ſight.</hi> Page 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dander and Sores</hi> Page 87, 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Dentifrices.</hi> Page 125, 126, 127</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>E</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>EYs faulty.</hi> Page 10</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eys red<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> Page 11, 86, 87</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119632:6"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eys pained.</hi> Page 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eys bloud-ſhed.</hi> Page 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Eys dropping.</hi> Page 86</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>F</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>FAce adorned.</hi> Page 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Face beautified.</hi> Page 17 <hi>to</hi> 25, 53, 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made fair.</hi> Page 25</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>whitend.</hi> Page 25 <hi>to</hi> 30, 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Freckels.</hi> Page 30, 31, 38</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fucus of the Duke of</hi> Millains. Page 26</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Face red.</hi> Page 31, 50, 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Face made red.</hi> Page 32</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made youthful.</hi> Page 35, 36</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Face bunched.</hi> Page 36, 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fatten the body.</hi> Page 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Face Coloured.</hi> Page 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Fair hands.</hi> Page 111</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>H</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>HAnds ſwell'd.</hi> Page 112</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Hair taken away.</hi> Page 74, 75, 76, 77</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to grow again.</hi> Page 64, 67, 69</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made thick.</hi> Page 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made black.</hi> Page 48, 60</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119632:7"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>to grow long.</hi> Page 5. 45. 57, 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made black.</hi> Page 6. 56. 60</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made yellow.</hi> Page 7, 8. 42. 46. 58</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made red.</hi> Page 8. 50. 58.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made white.</hi> Page 8. 50</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>increaſed.</hi> Page 9. 50, 51. 53, 54. 57</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ſhedding of it.</hi> Page 9, 10. 59, 60, 61 62</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>growth hindered.</hi> Page 10. 52. 74</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made of a Gold colour.</hi> Page 47, 48, 49</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>of a Saffron colour.</hi> Page 44, 45</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to curl it.</hi> Page 45 52</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>hardneſs of the feet.</hi> Page 121</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>I</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>ITalian Damask-water.</hi> Page 3</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>K</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>KNobs under the skin.</hi> Page 100</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>L</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>LEanneſs cauſed.</hi> Page 21. 39</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lotions or Lyes.</hi> Page 42</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lice in the Eye-brows.</hi> Page 82, 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Lice.</hi> Page 90</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Leprous.</hi> Page 100</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:7"/>
            <list>
               <head>M</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>MUsk-water.</hi> Page 1, 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Mark of the ſmall Pox.</hi> Page 38. 104</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>N</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>NIts.</hi> Page 91</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Nails leprous.</hi> Page 114</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>contuſed.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>cleft.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>ſhedding.</hi> Page 115</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>made to fall.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>O</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>OIntments brave-ſcented.</hi> Page 122, 123</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to yellow hairs.</hi> Page 78</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to whiten hair.</hi> Page 79. 81</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to black the hair.</hi> Page 79</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to black the beard.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to black gray hairs.</hi> Page 80</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to red the hairs.</hi> Page 81</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to curl the hair.</hi> Page 81, 82</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>for falling of the hair.</hi> Page 82, 83</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to make it grow again.</hi> Page 83</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>P</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>PImples in the face.</hi> Page 57, 92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pain from clefts.</hi> Page 119</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powders for the teeth.</hi> Page 124</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to whiten</hi> Page 127</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to faſten them</hi> Page 127</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Powders to adorn the hands.</hi> Page 126</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to whiten them.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perfumes.</hi> Page 129</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Pomanders for the Peſtilence.</hi> Page 133, 134</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Purging Pomander.</hi> Page 134</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>againſt the Plague.</hi> ibid.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perfuming Candels.</hi> Page 135</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Perfumes in the form of birds.</hi> Page 139</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>to make Candels or Troches.</hi> ibid.</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>R</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>REd hair cauſed.</hi> Page 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Red face cured.</hi> Page 32, 91, 98, 99</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Red face cauſed.</hi> Page 32, 33, 34, 35</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Ring-wormes.</hi> Page 37, 55, 95, 96, 97, 101</item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:8"/>
            <list>
               <head>S</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>SCabs in children.</hi> Page 106</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scalds and burns.</hi> Page 102 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>face ſmoothed after burns.</hi> Page 103</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scabby face.</hi> Page 99, 105</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Scurf in childrens heads.</hi> Page 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sores of the head.</hi> Page 87, 88</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Shedding of the beard</hi> &amp;c. Page 84</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweet Waters.</hi> Page 1, 2</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sight preſerved.</hi> Page 11</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>reſtored.</hi> Page 12</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>darkned.</hi> Page 13</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sun-burns.</hi> Page 25, 97, 100</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Skars of the face.</hi> Page 27, 28, 54</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Spots in the face.</hi> Page 55</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Speckels in the face.</hi> Page 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweet ſmelling Soap</hi> Page 122</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Soap muskified.</hi> Page 123, 136</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweet and white.</hi> Page 123, 124</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Sweet bags.</hi> Page 129</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>T</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>TEares of the eyes.</hi> Page 13, 85</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Teeth whiten'd.</hi> Page 13</item>
               <pb facs="tcp:119632:9"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>ſtrengthen'd.</hi> Page 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>faſten'd.</hi> Page 15</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Thickneſs of the face.</hi> Page 94</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Tetters.</hi> Page 102</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Troches for Perfumes.</hi> Page 137, 138</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>V</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>VIolet powder.</hi> Page 129, 130, 131, 132</item>
            </list>
            <list>
               <head>W</head>
               <item>
                  <hi>WHiten Hair.</hi> Page 8</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whiten Teeth.</hi> Page 13, 14</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Warts in the Face.</hi> Page 36. 95, 96 97</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wrinkles of the face.</hi> Page 36, 37. 54.92</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whiten Freckles.</hi> Page 37</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Worms and Scabs of the head.</hi> Page 89</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whiten Skars.</hi> Page 93</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Whiten the face.</hi> Page 108</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>the hands.</hi> Page 109, 110, 111</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Warts in the hand.</hi> Page 116</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Wrinkles after Childe-bearing.</hi> Page 120</item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:119632:9"/>
            <head>OF Ornamental VVaters.</head>
            <div type="part">
               <head>OF <hi>SWEET WATERS.</hi>
               </head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>SECTION I. <hi>A ſweet Water for the Body or Garments.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>TAke of Roſe-water, of Orange-flowers, of Myrtels, of Musk-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, each a pint, Powder of Orien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Orrice one ounce, Sivet a dram, mix them and boil them in a Glaſs veſſel, till a third part be waſted, then keep in a Glaſs veſſel very well ſtopt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another ſweet Water.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſe-water as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, of Musk one ſcruple, Sivet and Amber-greece, each a little, ſet them in a Glaſs veſſel by the fire till they are hot, then ſtop it well, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="2" facs="tcp:119632:10"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take roſe-water four pints, benjamin, ſtyrax, cloves, camphire, wood of aloes, each one ounce, musk and ſivet each one ſcruple, mix them in a glaſs veſſel well ſtopt, and boil them four hours in <hi>Balneo Mariae,</hi> then when it is cold, ſtrain it, and put it in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther glaſs veſſel well ſtopt, and ſet it in the Sun five dayes, adding fifteen grains more of musk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>The Authors Musk-water.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt roſe-water two pints, the beſt musk one ounce and a half, mix them and ſtill them in <hi>Bal. Mariae</hi> with a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry gentle fire, then keep it in a veſſel well ſtopt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of roſe-water twelve pints, water of lavender, cloves, cynamon, each one dram, mace, cardamoms, musk, ambergreece, each half a ſcruple, citron pill, yellow ſaun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, orrice, each half a dram, benjamin, ſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax-calamite, each one ſcruple, mix them all in a glaſs vial, and put them in <hi>Bal. Mariae</hi> ten dayes, then ſet it in the Sun fifteen days more, and it will be moſt excellent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of roſe-water four pints, lavender-water ſix ounces, the water of jaſmine-flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:119632:10"/>three pints, musk one ſcruple, mix them, and when they have been well ſtopt up ten dayes in a veſſel, then diſtil them in <hi>Bal. Mariae,</hi> and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A ſweet water of the Italians, which they call Damask-water.</head>
                  <p>TAke of cynamon one ounce, cloves half an ounce, ſweet-marjoram, roſemary, lavender, Bay-leaves, penny-royal, green province roſes, each a handful, mallego wine, roſe-water, each a pint and a half, cut the green things, powder the dry ones, and ſet them in the Sun ſix dayes, then diſtill them in a double veſſel: ſome adde to them citron pill, ſtorax calamite, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rice, each one dram, and flowers of jaſmine, they ſprinkle this water on their garments, linnen, hands, and noſtrils.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of cloves half an ounce, roſe-water a pint and half, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another pretty fancy.</head>
                  <p>Put twelve grains of musk into a veſſel with a narrow mouth, and put roſes or vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets into another veſſel, join the mouths of theſe veſſels together, and ſet them in the Sun, ſo that the roſes be uppermoſt, but let their mouths be parted with a linnen cloth;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:119632:11"/>ſome bruiſe the roſes a little, inſtead of musk you may uſe cloves and cynamon.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Let the loweſt part of the glaſs be filled with roſes, then ſtrew on lillies, and let every row have cloves ſtrewed on, and a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle musk, but let the uppermoſt row be of roſes, and ſo diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Or this way is made a moſt ſweet Water.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſes cut three pound, Cynamon, Cloves, each two drams, Camphure half a dram, Orrice root half an ounce, Nutmeg, Mace each two drams, put them in a glaſs, and pour upon them Candy-wine, Roſe, and Lavender-water, each three ounces, ſteep them eight dayes, and diſtil them, relliſh it with a ſcruple of Musk, and digeſt it in the Sun five dayes: you may adde alſo Storax-calamite and Benjamin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another compounded of the former.</head>
                  <p>Take of roſe-water a pint, of damask-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, of water of citron pills, of orrice, each one ounce, ſtorax-calamite half an ounce, cloves two drams, musk, amber-greece, ſivet, each one ſcruple, ſet them in the Sun fifteen dayes, ſhaking the glaſs every day, it is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent for the heart, brain, and ſtomach.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:119632:11"/>
                  <head>Of Waters that make the Hair grow long.</head>
                  <p>TAke of lard as much as is ſufficient, ſhave it very thin, then beat it in a marble morter, that it may be like paſte, then diſtil it in an Alembick, and you ſhall receive a white liquor, with which you muſt anoint the Hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to lengthen the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſtreined honey three pints, forty yelks of eggs, mix them and diſtil them, and anoint the hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh Maiden-hair bruiſed, one handful, of the beſt honey as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, mix them in the form of a paſte, and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Waters that colour the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make the Hair black.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Gum-arabick four ounces, chebul and emblick, myrobalanes, each half a pound; being powdred and diſtilled by a gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle fire, ſet them in the ſun two hours, and the head being waſht with a Ly, and dried, laſt of all wet the hairs with wine and ſalt, and waſh them with the diſtilled water, but let it not touch the skin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:119632:12"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gum-arabick four ounces, chebul, myrobalanes, roſes, each half a pound, being bruiſed, diſtil them with a gentle fire, and let the head, being firſt waſht with water, and not exactly dried again, be waſhed with this diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to black the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of privet and date-ſtones powder'd, each alike, of the water in which bean rindes and gauls have been boyled, as much as is ſufficient, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cypreſs nuts as many as are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, of red wine, red vinegar, each alike, boyl them together, and with this Decoction waſh the hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſpume of ſilver, as much as is ſufficient, of vinegar, or the juice of Citrons or Lemons as much as is ſufficient, boil them together half an hour, then waſh the hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the filings of iron, as much as is ſufficient, put it into the ſharpeſt vineger for ten days, then wet the hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the droſs of iron, filings of lead, as much as is ſufficient, boyl them in vineger
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:119632:12"/>till one half be waſted, ſtrein it, and waſh the hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Caper roots as much as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, boil them in Aſſes milk till a third be waſted, waſh the hairs, and let them alone all night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſalt Gemm, ſcales of braſs, privet, each alike, powder them, and diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſalt Gemm one pound, Romane Vitriol half a pound, ſalt Niter four ounces, the green roots of Celandine two pound, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing bruiſed and powdred, draw a water with an Alembick; caſt away that which comes out firſt, but the next colours the hairs, being firſt waſht and dried in the hot Sun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another moſt excellent.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aqua-fortis half an ounce, fine ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver two drams, mix them, and when the ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver is diſſolved, adde of Roſe-water three ounces, and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make the Hair yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt honey two pints, Gum-arabick two ounces, diſtil them with a gentle fire; the water which comes forth firſt, doth whiten the face, the ſecond and third makes the hair yellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="8" facs="tcp:119632:13"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſhaving<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Box, French La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Citron, Liquoriſh powder'd, the roots of Colts-foot, Maidenhair, each as much as is ſufficient, a little Saffron; boil them all to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till a third be waſted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agrimony one ounce, one ſtone of a horſe dried, boil them in ſpring water and diſtil them, and uſe it, the head being firſt waſht.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of vinegar two pints, ſalt niter half a pound, and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make Hair red.</head>
                  <p>Take of the water of raddiſh, of privet as much as is ſufficient, mix them and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make the Hair white.</head>
                  <p>Take of the greater Cento<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y four ounces, the lees of Allom eight ounces, Roch-allom, Gum-arabick, each two ounces; clean white ſoap, Gum-tragacanth, each four ounces, wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter ſix ounces, boil them to one half and ſtrein it, and the head being waſht with it, and dried by the ſun, laſt of all waſh it with Lye.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:119632:13"/>
               <head>Of Waters that increaſe the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make Hair grow.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the fleſh of ſnails, waſps, bees, horſleeches, burnt ſalt, each alike quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, put them in a glazed Veſſel, having ſmall holes at the bottom like a ſieve, and put under that another glazed veſſel, which may receive the moiſture which will drop forth in many days by degrees; take that and rub the places that have no hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water againſt ſhedding the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of pure honey, candy wine, a boyes urine, milk, each one pint, and diſtil a wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, with which you muſt waſh the places from whence the hairs fall.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another more effectual.</head>
                  <p>Take of mountain hyſſop, mountain cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mint, the leaves of ſouthernwood, each two handfuls, rich Candy wine, piſs, honey, milk, each two pints, muſtard-ſeed half a pound, powder thoſe things which ought to be, then mix them, and let them ſteep three days, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards diſtil the water; the uſe of which will ſuddenly bring forth a beard, and reſtore hair to bald places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of waters that hinder the growing of Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of the blood of Frogs, ſealed earth, ſumach, roſes, each a ſufficient quantity;
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:119632:14"/>vineger, juice of houſe-leek, each enough, ſteep them 24 hours, then diſtil them, and bathe the part often with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of a Cowes horn, roch-allom, black Poppy powder'd, each a ſufficient quantity, freſh Cows blood two pints, ſteep and diſtil them: uſe it every night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the decoction of Spurge made with vineger, unſlaked lime, and mallows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Henbane powder'd half a pound, put it in a moiſt place, and after a time ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding two ounces of the leaves of Orpin, diſtil it, and the hairs being pull'd out, often bathe the bare place with it.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Waters that take away the faults of the Eyes.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Againſt tears of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>TAke of ripe Strawberries, as much as is ſufficient, ſteep them in horſe dung, fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days, then diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the flowers of white thorn, the flowers or tops of Sallows, and the leaves of
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:119632:14"/>Sallow, each a ſufficient quantity, and diſtil them in a glaſs veſſel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Againſt redneſs of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take the juices of Celandine, Vervin, Rue, Fennel, each three ounces, the tops of Roſe-leaves as much as is ſufficient, Sugar-candy three ounces, the beſt Tutty and Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons blood, each four ounces, prepare them and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to preſerve the Sight.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe one ounce, Aloes two drams, Saffron one dram, Frankincenſe, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, Sarcocol, Camphure powder'd, each a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, put them into water and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fennel, Vervin, Eybright, Endive, Betony, red Roſes, Maidenhair, each three handfulls, bruiſe them and ſteep them a day in white wine, and then diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fennel, Celandine, Sage, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, Vervin, Rue, each a like quantity, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water againſt pains of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſe-water, Eyebright, Celandine, each one ounce, Tutty prepared one dram, mix them: the water from a vine cut, is good for the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:119632:15"/>
                  <head>A Water to reſtore the ſight.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fennel, Celandine, Vervin, Rue, leaves of Elecampan, each one handful, ſmall wilde Teaſel, Milfoil, each a handful, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure half a dram; diſtil then in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to dry up tears from the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tutty prepared one ounce, the blood-ſtone half an ounce; Dragons blood, Acacia, Antimony, each a dram, Camphure two ſcruples, ſealed earth a dram, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Maſtick, white Pepper, each half a ſcruple, water of Fennel, Eyebright, each one ounce; water of Violets, Roſes, each two ounces, old wine three ounces, boil them all in a double veſſel till half be conſumed, and then ſtrein it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water for the redneſs of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juice of unripe Grapes two ounces, Aloes a dram and half, binde it in a linnen Cloth, and ſteep it in the ſaid juice, and at night wet the eyes with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water againſt darkneſs of the ſight.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tutty prepared four ounces, the juice of unripe Grapes half an ounce, or five drams, ſet them in the Sun fifteen days, and adding half an ounce of Roſe-water, ſun it fifteen days more, and five days with Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bright water, afterwards powder the Tutty, and ſtrein it through a fine cotton cloth, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:119632:15"/>
                  <head>A Water againſt blood-ſhed Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take the pieces of a Marcheſite and burn them, then quench them in old, clear, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon oyl, powder them and diſtil them, and powder them over again with the reffuſe, and diſtil it again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Benjamin one ounce, pure white honey half a pint, Fennel and Rue water each twelve drams, water of Sweet-marjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram half an ounce, diſtil them in an Alem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water for ſwellings of the Eye-lids, and tears of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agrimony, Vervin, Fennel, Roſes, Celandine, each a ſufficient quantity, being all cut and ſprinkled with a little white wine, diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Waters that whiten the Teeth.</head>
               <p>TAke of ſalt Arabick, ſalt Gem, each half a pound, ſugar'd Allom three ounces, powder and diſtil them, and rub the teeth with a ſcarlet cloth dipt in the water.</p>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roch-allom, ſalt Niter, each one pound, a little Vinegar, being powder'd, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them with Vinegar, and diſtil them:
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:119632:16"/>to every ounce of the water, adde four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of juice of Lemons, and rub the teeth with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Allom ſix ounces, common Salt three ounces, Maſtick one ounce, Myrrhe half an ounce, Cloves ſix drams, mix and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil them, with which rub the teeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Salt clenſed and bruiſed, one pound, of Ice-alume one ounce, diſtil them in an Alembick, with an ounce of this water mix an ounce of plantane water, and rub the teeth with a Cotton cloth dipt in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another precious one.</head>
                  <p>Take of the firſt water of honey diſtilled, which is white, one pint, white Salt one ounce, Allom half a pound, ſalt Niter one ounce, water of the leaves of the Maſtick tree one pint, Maſtick, White-wine-vineger, each two ounces, diſtil them all in <hi>Bal: Mar:</hi> then rub the teeth with a Maſtick ſtick dipt in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Wine ſix ounces, the tops of Myrtil, Servas-tree, Cypreſs, each three ounces, Pomgranate flowers, the bark of Nut tree roots, Pellitory of Spain, Dragons blood, Date ſtones burnt, red Roſe-buds, Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, each one ounce, bruiſe them and diſtil
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:119632:16"/>them with a gentle fire; mix with two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this water, one ounce of burnt Harts-horn, and one ounce of Dragons blood, and ſet them in the ſun four days, then rub your teeth with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to ſtrengthen the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Take three Nutmegs, two roots of Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, a little Maſtick, Pellitory of Spain, ſweet Marjoram, Hyſſop, Mint, Roſemary, Sage, Salt, each half an ounce, put them all into ſweet wine, and let them boil till a third part be conſumed, then ſtrein it well, and uſe it hot.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Decoction to faſten the Teeth, cleanſe, and ſtrengthen the Gums.</head>
                  <p>Take of the water of Maſtick tree leaves, of Roſemary, diſtilled Vineger, each half a pint, Myrrhe, Maſtick, Bolearmenick, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons blood, burnt Alume, each one ounce, choice Cynamon half a dram, Rain-water three pints, mix them all and boil them with a very ſlow fire a quarter of an hour, adding of deſpumed Honey half a pint, a little Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin: waſh the teeth often with this, hold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing it in your mouth a while.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Waters that adorn the Face.</head>
               <p>TAke of the Crum of Barley-bread two pound, of Goats milk three pints, white
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:119632:17"/>wine half a pint, of the four greater cold ſeeds bruiſed, each three ounces, Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, Maſtick, Myrrhe, each one ounce, freſh Beans two pound, or Beans-flowers three ſmall handfuls, or of dryed Beans and red Cicers, each two pound; Rice half a pound, flowers of water Lillies, Violets, white Roſes, each two ſmall handfuls; ten Eggs, diſtil them in <hi>Bal. Mar.</hi> If you adde Turpentine before you diſtil it, the liquor will be the better, and preſerve the face the longer.</p>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Decoction of a Chicken, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, or Hen, three pints of the juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, one pint White wine vineger, half a pint Bean and Water-lilly-flowers, each three ſmall handfuls; Camphure and whites of Eggs, each two drams; mix them and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil them with an Alembick. In ſtead of the Decoction of a Capon or Hen, you may uſe the milk of a white Goat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bran ſeparated from the beſt grain, and of the ſtrongeſt Vineger, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, mix them and make a paſte; to which adde in the mixing twelve whites of Eggs, and diſtil it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:119632:17"/>
                  <head>A water to beautifie the Face.</head>
                  <p>Let the water made of the whites of new Eggs through a ſponge, with an equal quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity of Juice of Lemmons, be diſtilled as Roſe-water; afterwards adde to this water two ounces or thereabouts, of common Lye, and put into it a whole Lemmon bruiſed, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight days preſerve the Juice from it, and mix it with the water; let the face be firſt waſht with common water and dried, and then with this diſtilled water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſemary, white Tartar, white Wine, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A water to make the face very fair.</head>
                  <p>Take two young Pigeons, two pound of Veal, Spurge-ſeeds clenſed four ounces, Pine Nuts, ſweet and bitter Almonds, the Roots of white and blew Lillies, Beans bruiſed and cleanſed, Ox-gaul, the Root of Graſs Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, baſtard Dittany, each as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient; one Lemmon cut and cleanſed, the crum of white Bread ſteeped in Milk, Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>armoniack diſſolved in Vineger, Privet flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, each a ſufficient quantity; mix them and diſtil them with a gentle fire, and put a little Musk and Benjamin about the top
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:119632:18"/>of the neck of the Receiver, and keep it in a veſſel well ſtopt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of green Pine-nuts cleanſed and cut, as much as is ſufficient, put them in milk three days, every day adding new milk, then diſtil it with the things following, <hi>viz.</hi> Glaſs powder'd four ounces, red Coral three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Sugar-candy four ounces, Allom one ounce, mix them and make a powder, then take of Quickſilver killed with ſpittle, one ounce and a half, twelve new laid Eggs ſhels and all, broken and beaten together, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine nine times waſht four ounces, white Sea-periwinkles which Perfumers ſell, two ounces, Earth-ſnails fifty, bruiſe them all, and mix them, then put in part into a Glaſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goard, and then part of the powder, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards part of the Turpentine, laſt of all part of the ſnails, thus laying one upon another till the Goard be full, then adde a ſufficient quantity of white Wine, and with a ſlow fire diſtil it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Mellon Water to beautifie the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Mellons cleanſed from the Rine, as many as needs, and cut them into pieces a finger thick, then take of Sugar'd-allom four ounces, Burnt-allom, Quickſilver kill'd, each one ounce, white Sea-periwinkles
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:119632:18"/>two ounces, waſht Turpentine one ounce, twelve new laid Egges bruiſed with their ſhells, white Lemmons cut in pieces, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny as you pleaſe, Sugar four ounces, Goats milk, white wine, each a ſufficient quantity, put all theſe in a Glaſs-goard, one upon an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other, as hath been ſaid, then diſtil them with a gentle fire, and keep it in a glaſs veſſel for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A compleat Goard-water.</head>
                  <p>Take as many Goards as you pleaſe, clean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed from the Rines, and cut in round pieces, Sugar'd-alume ſix ounces, Alume one ounce, Myrrhe a dram, waſht Turpentine half an ounce, four new laid Eggs bruiſed, ſix Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſliced, Snailes as many as you pleaſe, white Wine a ſufficient quantity. Powder what is to be powder'd and mix them, laying the firſt row with Sugar, then with powders, the third with Snails, the laſt with Wine, Lemmons, and Eggs, and ſo diſtil them with a gentle fire, then keep it in a glaſs veſſel eight or fifteen days.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A water to ſet forth the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take two Calves feet, twelve pints of rain water, boyl away half, then adde one pound of Rice, the Crumb of one Loaf ſoftned in Milk, two pound of freſh Butter, ten whites of Eggs with the ſhells, mix them all and
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:119632:19"/>boyl them, then diſtil them; to which at laſt adde a little Camphure and Sugar'd-alume, and it will be excellent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Chryſocol or Borax two ounces, of Roche-alume, Sciſsil, Squammous, each one ounce, Camphure two drams, powder them all, then mix them, and put them in a glaſs vial filled with ſpring-water, and cloſe ſtopt, then ſet it to the fire two hours, then take it away, and when it is cold put it into another vial, adding two whites of new laid Eggs beaten well together with the Juice of unripe Grapes, and you will have a moſt compleat water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A water to adorn the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take Eggs cut in pieces, Orange-pills, the roots of Mellons, each as much as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, in a large veſſel with a long neck diſtil it by an Alembick with a ſtrong and careful fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bean-flowers ſix handfuls, Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon water one pint, Lilly roots eight ounces, Bean-flour one pound, Gum-arabick and Tragacanth, each one ounce, diſtil them, and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fennel, Rue, Vervin, Eyebright, Endive, Betony, Mountain-ſiler, red Roſes,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:119632:19"/>Maidenhair, each ſix handfuls, infuſe them a day and night in white wine, then diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Beanes cleanſed from the Rine, as much as you pleaſe, ſteep them in white Wine nine days, then bruiſe them and put them in again; to which adde Rice boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Goats milk, whites of Eggs, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix them all, &amp; diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh unripe Barley, Goats milk, whites of Egges, each a ſufficient quantity, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lemmons, dried Beans, ſteeped in Wine, Honey, Goats milk, the whites of Eggs, each a ſufficient quantity, mix and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cowes milk in the moneth of <hi>May</hi> two pints, three Oranges, five Lemmons, cut them ſmall, then adde of Alume, Sugar, each one ounce, mix them all, then diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the Face bright.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Crumb of white Bread two pound, Bean-flowers one pint, flowers of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, Water-lillies, Lillies, each four pints, Goats milk ſix drams, Venetian Flower-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luce
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:119632:20"/>one ounce, diſtil them in <hi>Balneo Mariae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine, the whiteſt Maſtick, Tutty prepared, Camphure, Alume, each four ounces, infuſe them three days in ſharp Vineger, then diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh Graſs-plantane one ounce, Rue one handful, Ground-ivy two handfuls, Borax one ounce, Wood of Aloes one dram, Styrax-calamite half an ounce, Musk half a ſcruple, Unguent three ounces, Camphure ſix drams, the fleſh of a Capon two ounces, Lemmon and Orange Pill, each one pound: diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Camphure three drams, red Alume, Borax, each ſix ounces, Musk two ſcruples, bruiſe them all, and then adde of Tartar one ounce and half, Roſe-water two pints, mix them well with a ſpattle, then diſtil it tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row a Filter, and keep it in a Vial well ſhut, then with a cloth take a drop or two of the water, and rub the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Waters that colour and whiten the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of wilde Rue, Fennel, Vervin, roots of Betony, Roſe-leaves, Maidenhair, each alike parts, ſteep them all night in fragrant white wine, and diſtil them in an Alembi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>k.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:119632:20"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cuckow-pintle as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, bruiſe the thicker parts, &amp; with Roſe-water dry them by the Sun three or four times, and pouring more Roſe-water on it, uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the white of an Egg, of rocky Borax, Salt, Roche-alume, each one ounce, powder them ſeverally, mix them with the whites of Eggs and diſtil them, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roche-alume powder'd three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, whites of Eggs as much as is ſufficient, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Flowers of Water-lilly, white Thorn, Elder, Beans, Violets, Maidenhair, each equal parts, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lytharge powder'd half a pound, boyl it in three ounces of white wine Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſtrein it through a cloth, and put it in a glaſs veſſel, then adde Camphure, Jaſmine, Alume, Borax, Oyl of Tartar, each alike parts, Roſe-water as much as is ſufficient, mix them and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another approved one of the Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of diſtilled Turpentine two pound, Frankincenſe three ounces, Maftick, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:119632:21"/>each half an ounce, powder them and mix them with Turpentine-water and diſtil them again; then take of freſh Hogs-greaſe melted, one pound, Cloves two drams, three Nutmegs, Gold one dram, Silver two drams, powder them finely and diſtil them in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bean-leaves ten handfuls, Roche-alume one pound and a half, Sugar'd-alume five drams; Endive, Alume, four ounces and a half, ſalt Niter three ounces, the Lees of Alume ſix ounces, Quickſilver killed three ounces; diſtil it with a ſlow fire, and when it begins to drop increaſe the fire.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Jaſmine, Alume, Borax, Roche-alume, all powder'd, each three ounces, the whites of Eggs as much as is ſufficient; diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of choice Silver, Quickſilver, each one ounce, powder them on a Marble<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, and adding a little Sublimate, ſet them in a moiſt place, and diſtil in an Alembick that which is melted.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the Face bright.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Lillies, Cuckow-pin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, Dragons, each half a pound; the Water of Bean-flowers a pint and a half, Roſe-wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eight ounces; diſtil them, adding Musk,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:119632:21"/>Cynamon, each two drams, and waſh the face twice a day.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to make the face look white.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Sulphur one ounce, white Frankincenſe two ounces, Camphure one dram, Roſe-water a pint, powder them and mix them, and ſet them in the ſun fifteen days, and waſh the face with it at night, but in the morning waſh it with the Decoction of Bran and Roſes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to whiten the Skin, and take away Sun-burn.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rain-water, the Juice of unripe Grapes, each alike quantity, boyl them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether till one half be conſumed, then whiſes it boyls adde ſo much Juice of Lemmons as was boyled away before, then when it is boy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led enough, take it from the fire and adde four whites of Eggs after it is cold, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to whiten Freckles, and Skars of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aquavitae four times diſtilled, three parts, the tops of Roſemary-flowers, two parts, ſteep them together a day and a night in a veſſel well ſtopt, then diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>The Water of a certain Noble-woman.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sublimate one ounce, Camphure one dram, powder them very wel, then infuſe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:119632:22"/>them in the Juice of Lemmons, Roſe-water, white Lilly, Goard, and Bean-flower-water, each half a pint, ſet them in the ſun fifteen days, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>
                     <hi>A Fucus or Colouring of the Duke of</hi> Millaines.</head>
                  <p>Take of Goats milk three pints, the Crum of two white Loaves, mix them together ſix hours, then adde Lemmons cleanſed from their pill, twelve whites of Eggs, Lime, Egg-ſhell, Venus-ſhell, each half an ounce, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure, Alume, red Corral, each two drams, Borax one ounce, Ceruſſe three ounces, mix them and diſtil them with care.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Flowers of Beans, of Water-lillies, each one pound, the Crum of white Bread, the Flower of Rice, of Orrice root, of wilde Cowcumber, each ſix ounces, honey one pint, white Wine, Spring-water, each three pints, mix them and diſtil them in <hi>Bal. Mariae,</hi> adding Goard-ſeeds cleanſed three ounces; Frankincenſe, Myrrhe, each one ounce, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to whiten Skars.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Orrice, wilde Cow-cumber, each three pound, the roots of Marſh mallows, Lillies, each two pound, ripe Grapes half a pound, Dittander roots three ounces,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:119632:22"/>the plant of Beanes, Pellitory of the wall, each one handful; the Flowers of Water-lillies, Mallows, each a ſmall handful; Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley bread one pound, ſteep them in white Wine or Goats whey, and diſtil them; then add of Raddiſh half an ounce, the four grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cold Seeds, each one dram, a Boys urine half a pint; ſet them in the ſun, and keep them for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Brimſtone, Salt, each half an ounce, Camphure, Tutty, each one dram; Roſe-water two ounces and a half, powder them and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to whiten the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Juice of Lemmons one ounce, of Venus-ſhell five ounces, ſteep them till they are diſſolved, then adde twelve Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons ſliced, ten whites of Eggs, Camphure, Borax, each one dram and a half; Water of Pine-apples half a pint, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſcum of Silver half a pound, white wine vineger three pints, boyl them till a third part be conſumed and diſtil them, then adde to the diſtilled water Camphure half an ounce, Endive, Alume, Oyl of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, Sugar'd-alume, each one ounce, leave them ſo till they are diſſolved, afterwards
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:119632:23"/>ſtrein it, and keep it ſafe for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water for a Red-face.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of round Birthwort, of white and red ſpatling poppy, each half an ounce, Orrice roots five ounces, Lilly roots ſix ounces, red Vetches, burnt Lupines, each half a pugil; Nutmeg, Cynamon, each half a dram, bitter Almonds bruiſed two ounces, Oyl of Tartar four ounces, Rain-water two pints, the blood of a Hare, as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, powder and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to whiten the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Roſes, the Flowers of Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-lillies, Elder, white Lillies, each one pound, Bean-flower water half a pint, the crum of bread a ſufficient quantity, twelve whites of Eggs; Frankincenſe two ounces, powder of Ceruſſe one pound, mix them and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Goats milk, Flour of Bread-corn, each a ſufficient quantity, work them into the form of a Loaf, and bake it in an Oven, then take the Crum of this Bread ſteeped in Goats milk, twelve whites of Eggs and diſtil them; adde to the diſtilled water, of Lime one ounce, Camphure, Sugar'd-alume, white Curral, each two drams, powder and mix them, and diſtil them again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:119632:23"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Tartar, white Wine, Roſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary flowers, each a ſufficient quantity; mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another very good one.</head>
                  <p>Take ſix new laid Eggs, half a pint of Mallego wine, young Pigeons, new Cheeſe without ſalt, each one, eight Oranges, Oyl of Tartar three ounces, Ceruſſe one ounce, bruiſe them, mix them and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take thirty Snailes, two pints of Goats milk, Hogs-greaſe three ounces, Camphure one dram; powder the Camphure by it ſelf, them bruiſe them all together &amp; diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the crum of white bread ſteeped in a ſufficient quantity of Goats or Aſſes milk, &amp; diſtil it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe two ounces, Frankincenſe, Maſtick, each half an ounce, white Ginger three drams, choice Cynamon, Sublimate, each two drams, Camphure one dram, the whites of Eggs one pint; powder them &amp; put them in the belly of a hen, adding three pints of Goats or Aſſes milk, and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to whiten the Face, and take away Freckles.</head>
                  <p>Take of Borax one ounce, Camphure one
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:119632:24"/>dram, Roche-alume three drams, Gum-ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, Tragacanth, each half an ounce; Sarco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>col, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>weet Aſa, each two ounces, Ceruſſe four ounces, powder them and adde the Water of Graſs-plantain; of Lilly flowers, of Broom flowers, of Water-lillies, each half a pint, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take four young Pigeons, freſh Butter, or the fat of Milk four ounces, the whites of twelve new laid Eggs, the root of Salomons-ſeal twelve drams, Borax two ounces, Flour of Cryſtal three ounces; Camphure, Endive, Alume, Sugar'd-alume, each half an ounce; water of Goards twelve ounces, water of ſowr Grapes three ounces; powder what is to be powder'd, then mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another excellent one of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take two pints of white wine vineger, one pint of Roſe-water, water of Orenge-pills, and Orenge-flowers, each ſix ounces, Whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hound one handful, honey half a pint, Musk three graines, Cloves four drams, Sugar'd-alume two ounces, Maſtick one ounce, pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take four Lemmons, Sugar-candy half an ounce, the Juice of wilde Grapes one pint four ounces, Aſſes milk half a pint, the whites
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:119632:24"/>of eight new laid Eggs, the Crum of white Bread three ounces, Camphure one dram and a half, Bean-flowers two pound, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of green Cane, the Juice of Gentian, of Houſleek, of Lemmons, each two ounces; Aſſes milk ſix ounces, Bean-flower water two pints, white Curral three ounces; Venus-ſhell diſſolved in Juice of Lemmons one ounce, Borax half an ounce; powder and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Waters that make the Face red.</head>
                  <p>To make the face ruddy, uſe ſhavings of Brazzeel diſſolved in Roſe-water with a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Camphure.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to colour the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take white young Pigeons, feed them fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen days with Pine-nuts, then open them, caſt away their heads, feet and bowels, and then take half a loaf, Sugar'd-alume as much as is ſufficient; five hundred leaves of Gold, three hundred of Silver, the crum of four white loaves ſoaked in the milk of ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, the marrow of a Calf, or Ox, or Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe one pound, mix them and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A red Water for the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take five and twenty whites of Eggs boyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed hard, a cup full of the milk of Figs, mix
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:119632:25"/>and diſtil them; then adde to this water for every pint, two ounces of Sciſsil-alume, Dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Grain half an ounce, Berries with which Silk is dyed, two drams; mix them and put them in a glaſs Vial well ſtopt, in dung, or in warm water for eight days, then take them out, and ſtrein and preſs them very well; which being done, add again as much Alume and Berries as before, and put it likewiſe in dung or warm water for eight days, and ſtrein them again as formerly; which when it is done three times, add half an ounce of Gum-arabick to one pint of water, &amp; leave it eight days in a warm place, as before; and laſt of all ſtrein it and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another more eaſe, and of leſs price.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Glew of fiſhes diſſolved five or ſix days in white wine, two ounces, Brazzeel ſlized, as much as is ſufficient, Spring-water a ſufficient quantity, mix and boyl them with a very ſlow fire till it is enough, then adde powder of Alume one ounce, Gum-arabick two drams; mix them, then taking it from the fire, keep it in a veſſel very well ſtopt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the face red.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Root of Salomons-ſeal ten ounces, the roots of Sows-bread five ounces, of Graſs-plantane or Cuckow-pintle, one ounce; clean Lard one ounce and a half, five
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:119632:25"/>Lemmons ſliced, the Crum of white Bread ſteeped in milk, as much as is ſufficient; Sub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>limate, Endive, Alume, each two ounces Roche-alume one ounce and a half, Venus ſhell diſſolved in the Juice of Lemmons, one ounce; mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of the greater Graſs-plantane cleanſed and bruiſed, as much as is ſufficient, Spring-water a ſufficient quantity; mix and boyl them till a fourth part be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, then take it from the fire, and keep it in a veſſel well ſtopt: alſo the water diſtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led from the roots of Graſs-plantane, the roots of Bryony, and the roots of Sows-bread do make the face red.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Dragons, or Graſs plantane, of white Lillies, of freſh Lard, each half a pound; Bean-flower water four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Roſe-water eight ounces, Musk, Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nom, each one dram; powder and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Borax one dram, Sublimate two ounces, Camphure half a dram, ſalt Gem one dram, ſalt Alkali, Roche-alume, Endive, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume, each two ounces; Plumed-alume, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar'd-alume, each half an ounce, Roſe-water as much as is ſufficient; boyl them in a glaſs
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:119632:26"/>veſſel till half be conſumed, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to colour the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of Aquavitae, Bean-flower water, Roſe-water, each four ounces; water of the Flowers of Water-lillies ſix ounces, Tragacanth powder'd one dram, mix them and ſet them in the ſun for ſix or eight days, then ſtrein it and keep it for uſe: let the face be firſt waſhed before you uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Goats milk two pints, one hot white Loaf, the root of Dragons, or Graſs-plantane, the root of Salomons-ſeal, each half a pound; the head of one Wether cut, Borax, Endive, Alume, each half an ounce, the Juice of Lemmons, Venus-ſhell diſſol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in the ſame, Ceruſſe, each one ounce; Litharge, Sublimate, each half an ounce; pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der what is to be powder'd, and cut ſmall that which is to be cut, then mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ceruſſe two ounces, Sublimate one ounce, Plumed-alume, Endive, Alume, each half an ounce, Borax two drams, Camphure one dram Sugar-candy two ſcruples, Roche-alume one ſcruple; powder them and tye them up in a linnen cloth, then adde a young white Pigeon cleanſed and cut in ſmall pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:119632:26"/>boyl them all together in Goats or Aſſes milk till the fleſh be ſevered from the bones, afterwards diſtil them all in an Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Snails, ſalt Gem, Juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, each a ſufficient quantity, being cut and powder'd mix them well, and diſtil them in <hi>Balneo Mariae.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take 12 Lemons ſliced, the Juice of Bryo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, white wine, each a ſufficient quantity, the whites of three Eggs, mix and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Waters that black the Face.</head>
                  <p>With Chymical Inſtruments extract a moſt clear water, from green Walnut-ſhells and Gaules; with which if you wet the face or hands, they grow black by degrees, like to an Aethiopian; which if afterwards you would reſtore to their former whiteneſs, you muſt diſtil Vineger, Juice of Lemmons and Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phonia, and waſhing with that will take off the blackneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Waters that make the face youthful.</head>
                  <p>Take of Live-ſulphur one ounce, Oliba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Myrrhe, each two ounces, Ambergreece ſix drams, powder and mix them, adding a pint of Roſe-water, then diſtil them and keep the water in a veſſel well ſtopr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>; which if any one will uſe, at night when he goes to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:119632:27"/>bed let him waſh his face, and in the morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with ſpring water, and it will be moſt comely.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take two Calves feet, River-water nine quarts, boyl them till one half be waſted, then adde one pound of Rice, the crum of a Loaf mollified in milk, freſh Butter two pound, ten whites of Eggs with their ſhels, mix them all and boyl them, then diſtil all the water from them; to which add at laſt Camphure and Sugar'd-alume, each a little, and it will be excellent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take two ounces of Aquavitae, Bean-flower water, and Roſe-water, each four ounces; water of Water-lillies ſix ounces, mix them all, and adde to them one dram of the whiteſt Tragacanth, ſet it in the ſun ſix dayes, then ſtrein it through a fine linen cloth: you muſt uſe it in the morning, and not wipe it off.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Waters that take away ſpots in the Face.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water for Warts and bunchings out in the Face.</head>
                  <p>TAke of ſalt Ammoniack, Roman Vitriol, Verdegreaſe, each two ounces, red A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lume an ounce, unſlaked Lime half an ounce,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:119632:27"/>diſtil them in a glaſs Alembick; caſt away the firſt liquor, the ſecond is more effectual, and to be kept for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water for wrinkles of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Decoction of Bryony and Figs, each alike quantity, &amp; waſh the face with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For Ring-worms of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take 4 ounces of the water of ſowr Dock, Borax three drams, common ſalt one dram, Vineger of Squills one ounce, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To prevent them.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt white Wine-vineger three ounces, the Juice of ſowr Dock, the Juice of Lemmons, each three drams, Lytharge of Gold one pound, boyl them gently, then di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtil them and keep it for uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to whiten the Specks or Frec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kels of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take three parts of the beſt Aquavitae, two parts of Roſemary-flower, ſteep them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a day and a night, then diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water that takes away all troubles what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever from the Face.</head>
                  <p>Work the Flour of Bread-corn with Goats milk, bake a Loaf of it gently, and draw it before it be too much, leave the crum of this bread broken into ſmall pieces, ſteeping in freſh Goats milk for ſix hours, mix with it the water of twelve whites of Eggs made with a
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:119632:28"/>ſpunge, Egg-ſhells calcined one ounce, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure, Sugar'd-alume, white Corral, each two ounces; powder them all, incorporate them with the liquors, and diſtil them in a glaſs Alembick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Wrinckles.</head>
                  <p>Take one Pomegranate, hollow it and cleanſe it from the inward parts, then infuſe it in whey and wine, each a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, and boyl them till the wine be evapo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated, then uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For Freckles of the face.</head>
                  <p>Take Roſe-water, Juice of Lemmons, each eight ounces Sublimate two drams, four whites of Eggs, mix them all well, then ſet it in the ſun for eight days, and keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take four pints of Aſſes milk, one pint of white Wine, the crum of two new Loaves, twelve Eggs with their ſhells, Sugar-candy three drams, bruiſe and diſtil them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Water to take away the marks of the Small-pox.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maſtick, Myrrhe, Hepatick-Aloes, Nard, Dragons blood, Olibanum, Opoponax, Bdellium, Carpobalſame, Saffron, Gum-ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, liquid Styrax, each two drams and a half, powder them all, and with Turpentine the weight of them all, diſtil a liquor with
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:119632:28"/>glaſs inſtrumen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s. Water from Beans, Calves, Ram<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, Hogs feet, of Honey, of the root of Graſs-plantane, Lemmons, O enges, Bean-flowers, Egg-ſhells, will do the ſame.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Potions that adorn the Body.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Potion to make the Body fat.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the flour of Vetches, Beans, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley, Rice, each alike parts, flour of Len<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tils, white Poppy, each half as much: flour of bread corn, Turky-millet, each alike quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, Sugar twice as much, boyl them in a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity of Sheeps milk, of which let him take one cup every morning faſting, ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping upon it half an hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Milk, Spring-water, each one pint, boyl them together till the water be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, then adde Sugar of Penidies, freſh Butter, each one ounce, Oyl of ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds newly drawn, half an ounce, give them one boyling more, and ſo let it be taken fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting, and ſleeping upon it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Drink to make the body lean.</head>
                  <p>Take of round Birthwort one dram, the leſſer Centory one ſcruple, Gentian, Poly, Parſley, each three drams, powder them and take them with white Wine faſting.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="40" facs="tcp:119632:29"/>
                  <head>Of Baths to mundifie the Body.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pellitory of the wall, Mallows, Bears-breech, Violet leaves, each one hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, whole Barley two pugils; Violet, Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memel-flowers, each three pugils; make a Decoction in rain-water, and with that make a Bath, with which waſh faſting, afterwards when the Body hath ſweated in the bed, wipe it carefully.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to cleanſe the Body, and make it comely.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sage, Lavender-flowers, Roſe-flowers, each two handfuls, a little Salt, boyl them in water or in a Lye, and make a Bath not too hot, in which bathe the body two hours before meat.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſe-water, Vineger, Salt, each as much as is ſufficient, make a Decoction with Spring-water; of which take two cups full, and a ſufficient quantity of Bran, mix them and rub the body with it, then waſh with warm water, or with a ſweet Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Bath for faults of the Skin in Cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lerick Bodies.</head>
                  <p>Take of Barley cleanſed three pugils, of Marſh-mallows, Mallows, Violet leaves, each three handfuls, Beets, Pellitory of the wall, Bugloſs, Burrage, each one handful, the ſeeds
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:119632:29"/>of Goard, Citrul, Mellon, Cowcumber, Flax, Fenigreek, each two drams, flowers of Vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, Roſes, Water-lillies, Lillies, each two handfuls; make a Decoction with the head and feet of a ram, and make a warm Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A ſtronger Bath for faults of the Skin.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Lillies, Graſs-plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, Bryony, each one pound, Burrage, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, Fumitory, Sope-wort, each two hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fulls, Pellitory of the Wall, Maidenhair, Mallows, Violet leaves, each one handful; whole Barley, Beans blanched, Rice, each three ounces; Flowers of Melilot, Chame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel, Roſemary, Mallowes, Violets, each two pugils; roots of Orrice, Niter, each a ſufficient quantity, make a Decoction for a Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A ſweet-ſcented Bath for Noble-women.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſes, Citron pill, Citron flowers, Orenge flowers, Jaſmine, Bays, Roſemary, Lavender, Mint, Pennyroyal, Spring-water, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther gently and make a Bath, to which adde Oyl of Spike ſix drops, Musk five grains, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergreece three grains, ſweet Aſa one ounce; let her go into the Bath two houres before meat.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:119632:30"/>
               <head>Of Lotions or Lyes that adorn the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to make the Hair fair.</head>
                  <p>IF you would have your hair fair, and ſweet cented, waſh your head with <hi>Galens</hi> Lye, called <hi>The diſtilled Lye,</hi> which is made of a little aſhes of a Vine burnt, of the Knots of Ba ley ſtraw, and liquoriſh Sowes-bread, and whiles the head is combed, ſprinkle the hair with the powder of Cloves, Roſes, Nutmeg, Cardamom and Galingale, with Roſe-water, dipping the Comb alſo in it: alſo they are made fair, being often waſht with the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coction of Beech-tree nuts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the Hair yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take of Dyers Madder, yellow French La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Maidenhair, Wormwood, Lupines, each a ſufficient quantity, put them in water or a Lye, in a glaſs veſſel for nine days, ſtir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it every day twice, and ſteep a ſpunge in it, with which waſh the hair, and after it is dryed, waſh it with warm water and ſoap.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Hair of a Gold colour.</head>
                  <p>Take of Barley ſtraw, the rine of Liquoriſh, ſhavings of Box, leaves of Box, Saffron, Cum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>min, each a ſufficient quantity; the Lye of the aſhes of prunings of Vines, as much as is ſufficient, boyl them all well and make a
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:119632:30"/>Lye, with which if the hairs be often waſht, they will be exceeding yellow, and like the colour of gold.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make it yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye of Vines, as much as is ſufficient, to waſh the hairs once, the flowers of Mullein, French Lavender, the roots of Celandine, each one pugil, boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; let the head be firſt waſht with a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Lye, and being dried, waſh it with this decoction, and dry it by degrees with hot lin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nen clothes. The Italian women boyl in a common lye the flowers of French Lavender bruiſed, and the ſhavings of yellow Sanders.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſhavings of Box, French La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vender, Citron pill, Liquoriſh powder'd, the roots of Coltsfoot, Maidenhair, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, a little Saffron, boyl them in water till a third part be conſumed, ſtrein it and waſh the head, and anoint the comb with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Barley ſtraw, as much as is ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient, Myrtle-flowers, ſhavings of Box, Saf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fron, Cummin, Privet, each three drams, boyl them in a Lye of Vines, with which waſh the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lupines one ounce and a half,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:119632:31"/>Myrrhe one ounce, Stavesacer, white Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, each half an ounce, boyl them in a Lye, and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Oat ſtraw, the roots of Celan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine, Agrimony, the ſhavings of Box, Vine-aſhes, Oat aſhes, each a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, make a Lye with warm water, and waſh the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to dye the hair of a Saffron colour.</head>
                  <p>Take Lye in which a little Rubarb hath bin diſſolv'd, wil dye the hair of a Saffron colour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Raw Lupines anointed on the hair with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and Niter, do make them yellow, ſaith <hi>Galen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lupines powder'd, Myrrhe, each five drams, ſalt Niter, white Tartar burnt, each three drams; the Lye of prunings of Vines, a ſufficient quantity, mix them and with this waſh the haires in the ſun with a ſpunge or comb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the rine of Barberries half an ounce, the root of Liquoriſh two ounces and a half, Spleen-wort, Oakfern, each one handful; make a Decoction in water or Lye, ſtrein it, and to one pound, adde common honey one ounce, water of Graſs-plantane, of Cuckow-pintle,
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:119632:31"/>each half an ounce, mix them and with a ſpunge or comb dye the hairs in the ſun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tartar calcined half an ounce, the roots of privet two ounces, Raddiſh roots three ounces, bruiſe them well &amp; boyl them, rub the hairs when you go to bed, and in the morning waſh it with the Lye of Vines.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Lye of the aſhes of the wood of Ivy unbarked, waſh the head often, and the hair will become yellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to make the hair red and curled.</head>
                  <p>In <hi>Bononia</hi> they waſh them in a Lye of prunings of Vines, in which the ſhavings of Box and Citron pill are ſteeped. In <hi>Ita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> alſo they ſay, that a Gentian root will do the ſame.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to make the hair yellow, bright, and long; and to help the Memory.</head>
                  <p>Take ſo much common Lye as will waſh the head ten times, ſix ſweet Orange pills, Citron pill as much as you pleaſe, Chame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mel flowers, Bay-leaves, Maidenhair, each one handful, Agrymony half a handful, Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley ſtraw cut, three handfuls, dry Lupines a handful, Fenigreek two handfuls, burnt Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar half a pound, Flowers of Matweed five
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:119632:32"/>handfuls, mix them and put them in ſome great veſſel, and keep it for your uſe: when you would uſe it, take a little out of the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, and heat it in another veſſel, and adde if you pleaſe, a little Myrrhe and Cynamon, and ſo it will be excellent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lotion for the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the lees of Alume eight ounces, Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tory one pound, Gum-arabick, Starch-corn, each three ounces, white Soap one ounce, River-water one pint, mix them and boyl them till a fourth part be waſted; after that the head hath been waſht with a Lye, let this water dye them with a ſpunge in the ſun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to make the hair yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take the flowers of Mullein one handful, Fenigreek two ounces, Vine aſhes, the wood of Ivy aſhes, each one handful, Rain-water ten points, boyl them together till one half be conſumed; ſtrein it, and adde four pound of the whiteſt Soap, Saffron two drams, mix them and ſet them in the ſun for one month, with which dye the hair in the ſun with a ſpunge or comb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye made of the aſhes of the wood of Ivy, as much as is ſufficient, the flowers of Mullein, St. Johns-wort, Feni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greek, each as much as is ſufficient, boyl
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:119632:32"/>them and make a Lye, with which waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye of prunings of Vines, the flowers of Mullein, French Lavender, the ſhavings of Butchers-broom, the roots of Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>landine, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lye to make a Gold colour.</head>
                  <p>Powder the ſtems and roots of Coleworts, and mix them with the ſhavings of Box or Ivory powder'd, and with thoſe Powders make a Lye, which will do the buſineſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye of Vine aſhes, as much as is ſufficient, Saffron, white Soap, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye of prunings of Vines, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyroyal, each a ſufficient quantity; mix, boyl them, and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Lye made of Colewort aſhes, a ſufficient quantity, the roots of Agrimony, Salt, each as much as will ſuffice, a little A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes, boyl them together, then adde Saffron, Rubarb powder'd, each a little, mix them and make a Lye, with which waſh the head at night, and wrap it up with a hor linen cloth, and next morning they will be yellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="48" facs="tcp:119632:33"/>
                  <head>Of Lyes that colour the Hair black.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Juice of the rine of Walnuts, three pints, Litharge powder'd one pound, mix them together with a Lye, and waſh the hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the rines of Fig-tree, Gauls, Date<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree, Brambles, Cypreſs, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make a Lye to waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fig-tree leaves, of black Vine, of Mulberry leaves, each one pound, Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water a ſufficient quantity, ſteep them one day, then boyl them and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of common Lye, leaves of Beets one handful, Sage three or four handfuls, Myrrhe, Bay-leaves, the rines of green Nuts, each a ſufficient quantity, mix and boyl them, and ſo waſh the head; then in the end waſh the face and neck with a ſimple Lye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrtle-berries, Sumach, Sage, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Nuts, Citrine, and Chebul, Myrobalans, common Lye, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them all together till a third part be conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and make a Lye to waſh the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:119632:33"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Indian Myrobalanes, Gauls, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Nuts, Pomegranate flowers, Myrtle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berries, each one ounce; Roche-alume half an ounce, ſalt Gem one dram, powder them and boyl them in water, with which waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Lye a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, Litharge of Gold one pound, boyl them awhile together, then take them from the fire, and adde Oyl of Tartar half an ounce, mix them and anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Lye two parts, the aſhes of Maſt-tree, ſalt Niter, each one part, mix them and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to colour the hair and beard.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſcum of Silver, burnt Braſs, each one part, of the ſtrongeſt Lye four parts, boyl them with a gentle fire, and when it riſes in bubbles, waſh the hair, and when they are drid again, ſprinkle them with warm water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the water of Stillatory, in which put four iron needles till they are diſſolved, and yellow Arſnick powder'd, and with a feather wet the comb with the ſame water, and comb the hair by the fire ſide, or in the ſun, but ſo as it touch not the skin.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="50" facs="tcp:119632:34"/>
                  <head>Of Lyes to colour the Hair red.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lupines powder'd ten drams, Myrrhe half a dram, the flowers of Sallow, burnt Tartar, each three drams, being pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, put them in a Lye, and boyl them till they are thick, with which dye the hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sumach two ounces, Gauls three ounces, Madder two ounces, Maidenhair, Wormwood, each one ounce, Lupines husked two handfuls, water ten pints, ſteep them for ſome days, then waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Lyes that colour the Hair white.</head>
                  <p>Take of the greater Centory four ounces, the Lees of Alume eight ounces, Roche-alume, Gum-arabick, each two ounces, clean white Soap, Gum-tragacanth, each four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, clear water ſix ounces, boyl half away then ſtrein it, and the head being waſht with that, and dried in the ſun, laſt of all waſh it with a Lye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Vine aſhes one pound, water ſix pints, and make a Lye.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Lyes to lengthen the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agrimony, Elm bark, Vervin, Rain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water, each a ſufficient quantity, mix and boil them till a third part be waſted, with which waſh the hair once every week.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="51" facs="tcp:119632:34"/>
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the rine of Sallow, Wormwood, Sou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thernwood, dried Roſes, Water, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix and ſteep them for a whole Friday and Sunday, boyl them till a third part be waſted, and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of Goats Milk Whey, the aſhes of a Cane, Flax-ſeed, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them together, ſtrein it, and make a Lotion for the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maidenhair, Emblick, Myrobalanes, Sorrel, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them in water, ſtrein it and adde a little Myrrhe, and make a Lotion for the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Lyes to increaſe the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agrimony, Elm bark, the roots of Sallow, Southernwood, Marſh-mallowes, white Popler buds, aſhes of Colewort-ſtalks, water, each a ſufficient quantity; make a Lye to waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bears-breech, common Lye, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the hair thick.</head>
                  <p>Take of Agrimony, Elm bark, roots of Vervin, roots of Sallow, Southernwood,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:119632:35"/>Flax-ſeed burnt, Cane-roots, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, mix them all and boyl them in Goats milk or water, and waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lotion to increaſe the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maidenhair three ounces, Labda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, Myrtle, a Goard burnt, each one ounce, ten pints of water, powder them and ſteep them twenty days, every day mixing them, then boyl them till a third part be conſumed, and make a Lye to waſh the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of white Wine, the aſhes of Maidenhair burnt, a pretty good quantity, boil them together to waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lotion to hinder the growth of hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the Decoction of Spurge, mixt with Vineger, unſlaked Lime, and Mallows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Lotion to make the hair curl.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Marſh-mallows boyled in water, preſs them and ſtrein them, and add to it the ſeed of Flax, Fleawort, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, afterwards ſtrein it and mix it exactly, and rhen waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the flour of Fenegrick, Henbane, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge of gold, each equal parts, put them in a Lye, with which waſh the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Fern, the leaves of
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:119632:35"/>Beets, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them together till a third part be conſumed, then take it from the fire, and add of Gum-ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick as much as will ſuffice, mix them and make a Lotion, with which waſh the hair, and when they are dried, wet them with Oyl of Myrtles.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Oyls that adorn the Face.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to beautifie and take away black Puſtels.</head>
                  <p>TAke Tartar of white Wine broke into pieces, wrapt in a linnen cloth wet with ſtrong vineger, or wrapt in Colewort leaves and courſe Flax under the hot aſhes, till it may be reduced into an exact Powder; which ſet in an earthen veſſel bending downwards four or five dayes in the ſun, then with the Oyl that doth diſtil anoint the face, it being firſt waſht with warm water and Soap, and then dried with Bran-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another uſed by the Venetian Curtizans.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Tartar half a pound, powder it and dry it as they do ſalt, then take that ſalt and put it within the whites of Egges boyled.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to clear and whiten the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take twelve yelks of Eggs boyled hard,
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:119632:36"/>half a cup of Oyl of the Maſtick tree, a dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble quantity of Turpentine waſht, mix them and boyl them awhile together, then draw an Oyl with a preſs, with which anoint the face at night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to cure a red Face.</head>
                  <p>Take four ounces of Peach Kernels, Goard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed two ounces, bruiſe them &amp; make an Oyl to anoint the face morning and evening.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to colour the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Oyl, Roſemary-flowers, each one part, mix them and put them in a glaſs vial under horſe dung, for three weeks or a moneth, then ſtrein it and ſet it in the ſun for ſome days, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Oyls to take away the wrinkles of the face.</head>
                  <p>Oyl of Turky-miller, and the Decoction of its Berries, do diſtend, mollifie, and conſoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>date wrinkles; alſo Oyl of Nuts is good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Oyl of Tartar takes away wrinckles of the face; alſo Oyl of bitter Almonds, and Oyl of Lillies.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to take away Skars.</head>
                  <p>Oyl of Dates avails much to blot out the marks of the Skars.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl for Pimples of the face.</head>
                  <p>Bruiſe Walnuts and boyl them, till an Oyl from them doth ſwim above water, which uſe</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="55" facs="tcp:119632:36"/>
                  <head>An Oyl for Spots in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſemary-ſlowers, as much as is ſufficient, bury them in a glaſs veſſel under dung ſafe from rain, keep it thirty days, and that which is diſſolved, expoſe to the ſun for nine days, with powder of Polypodie mixt, as much as you can take in three fingers; of which take every day for a moneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl for a Ringworm in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take a green live Lizard, boyl it in wine and oyl, till the wine be conſumed, then ſtrein it and uſe it. Oyl of Mezereon, Oyl of Aſh, Oyl of Eggs, do likewiſe take away all ſpots and ſpeckles of the face.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Oyls to preſerve and increaſe the Hair.</head>
               <p>FIll a wild Goard, (caſting away that which is in it) with Oyl of Bayes, and adding Henbane-feed and yellow Arſnick, anoint the hairs.</p>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To increaſe the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of Marſh-mallows, a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity, boyl them in common Oyl, with which anoint the hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Alſo the Oyl of Earth-vvorms doth increaſe the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="56" facs="tcp:119632:37"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſowr Grapes juiced, ſix ounces, Oyl of Maſtick, Oyl of Myrtle, Oyl of Lab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum, each two ounces, Maidenhair four ounces, boyl them till the Juice of Grapes be conſumed, and anoint the hair with the Oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a wilde Goard cleanſed from the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward parts, in the hollow of which put as much Oyl of Maſtick-tree as it can contain, a little Saffron, boyl them together till a third part be conſumed, and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Oyl of Southernwood doth produce hair.</head>
                  <p>It is made as Oyl of Rue, it is good to cauſe hair grow; and in ſhedding of hair it is an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ointed with Labdanum and Bears fat.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Oyls that colour the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to black it.</head>
                  <p>OYl made of green Lizards doth black the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Privet, Vitriol, common Oyl, each a ſufficient quantity, ſet them to the fire till they begin to boyl, then keep it to anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Juice of the rines of Sallow, common oyl, or Oyl of Coſtmary, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix them and anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:119632:37"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a hundred green Nuts, common Oyl a pint and a half, liquid Alume three pound, put all theſe together into a new earthen veſſel firſt made wet, and being carefully anointed about, ſet is in a place not too moiſt nor too hot, and let it be under the earth three moneths, then take it away and uſe the Oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of red Poppy, the Juice of green Nuts, Oyl of Myrtles, Oyl of Coſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mary, each one part, boyl it a while and an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Emblick, Myrobalanes one ounce, of the binding Bean-tree ten drams, Gauls, Acorn-cups, Myrtle-berries, Sumach, each ten drams, Oyl of unripe Olives, Oyl of ſweet Almonds, each eleven ounces, Labda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num three ounces, a little Vineger; mix them and boyl it till the Vineger be conſumed, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>If a wilde Goard, the ſeeds being taken out, be filled with Oyl, or as others will have it, with Oyl of Bays, and the whole ſeeds of black Henbane, and be ſet ſo a day and a night in a warm place, and the hairs be anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the oyl, it blacks them, and keeps off gray hairs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:119632:38"/>
                  <head>An Oyl to make the hair yellow.</head>
                  <p>Take of choice Myrrhe, the root of the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Madder, the root of Celandine, each alike parts, powder them all, and boyl them in oyl in which ſhavings or pieces of Box and Saftron have been firſt boyled; with this an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the hair, being often waſht with a Lye made of the ſpirits of Beans and Barley.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make them long, yellow, and as bright as Gold.</head>
                  <p>Take of Oyl of Turkey-millet one mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, flowers of Matweed cut, three ounces; white Lilly-ſeeds one ounce, Turmerick two drams, Saffron half a dram, Cynamon, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin, Musk, Sivet, each a little; mix them all and put them in a glaſs Vial, and ſet it in the ſun a whole ſummer; with this Oyl an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the comb, then comb the hair in the ſun, and cover the head combed with a warm cloth gen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ly that it do not preſs it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to dye the hair red.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Tartar, Oyl of Maſtick, Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zen of the Pine-tree, each as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient, mix and anoint the hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Oyls to lengthen the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take three green Lizards, Oyl of Myrtles, as much as is ſufficient, boyl them together till their fleſh be diſſolved, and anoint the comb.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="59" facs="tcp:119632:38"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of Emblick, Myrobalanes, a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, ſteep them in Oyl of Turky-millet till they ſwell, then boyl them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther a quarter of an hour.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Oyl to preſerve Travellers from cold.</head>
                  <p>Firſt chafe the extream parts well, then an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint them with the oyl of Euphorbium hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, with oyl of Pellitory of Spain, and oyl of Peppers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments that hinder ſhedding the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum ſteeped in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>owr wine, and powder'd, a ſufficient quantity, Oyl of Myrtles what will ſuffice; mix them and make an Unguent, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h which anoint the hair before bathing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take two parts of Labdanum, Oyl of Myr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tles, Wine, each a ſufficient quantity, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair one part, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrtle-berries, Labdanum, each three ounces; with the Decoction of bind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Bean-tree, boyl it to a thickneſs, then adde Oyl of Nard or Myrtles, a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to preſerve the hair, and make them black.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrtle-berries, ſeeds of Smallage,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:119632:39"/>Beets, ſprouts of Myrtles, each a pint and a half; Maidenhair, Labdanum, each twelve ounces, black wine ſeven pints, boyl them till they are wholly diſſolved; and when a third part is remaining, adde four pints and a half of Oyl of Myrtles, and boyl it again till it is thick.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to preſerve the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take a pint and a half of Candy-wine ſod<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, Labdanum one ounce, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ine of Pine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuts burnt, two ounces; Maidenhair burnt, one ounce, Bears-greaſe one pound, juice of Beets three cups full, boyl the Labdanum and Wine till they come into one body, then put in the reſt, and taking them away, keep it in a leaden veſſel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Small age ſeeds two ounces, Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair, Frankincenſe, each two ounces, fifteen Walnuts, Labdanum two ounces, rines of Pine-nuts one pound, put them all into a new earthen veſſel well ſtopt with clay, and burn them in the furnace of a bath, then take them out and powder them, and add of Bears fat one pound, work them into a body and put them in an oaken or Cypreſs Box; and at time of uſe, take as much as will be needful, and beat it up with what ſweet ointment you pleaſe, &amp; anoint the head with it twice a day</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="61" facs="tcp:119632:39"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of dried Coleworts a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, powder it, and with water bring it into the form of an Unguent, and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Labdanum ſprinkled with ſowr wine, powder it, and with Oyl of Myrtles and wine poured to it by courſe, bring it to the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Honey, and anoint the head with it before and after a bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Juice of ſowr Grapes, or unripe wine, a pint and a half, Labdanum one ounce, the rine of Pine-nuts burnt two ounces, Maiden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hair burnt three ounces, the fat of a Bear or Duck four ounces, Juice of Night-ſhade half an ounce; boyl the Wine and Labdanum to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, then add the reſt and keep it for uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum, Maidenhair, Oyl of Myrtles, each one dram, Rue two drams, old wine a ſufficient quantity, bruiſe and mix them, then adde enough Bears fat, and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Archigene's <hi>Ointment againſt falling of the Hair.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum, Wormwood, each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, ten Juniper-berries, Oyl as much as is ſufficient; bruiſe, mix them, and reduce
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:119632:40"/>them into the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame Authors.</head>
                  <p>Take of black Maidenhair, black Myrtles, each equal parts, the double quantity of Gauls; with Oyl of Maſtick or Myrtles, bring to the thickneſs of Honey, and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Frankincenſe, Vitriol, Gauls, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair, each equal parts, powder them in the ſun and bring them with Wine to the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Honey, or boyl them gently till they look black, then mix them with Oyl of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick or Myrtles, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Wormwood, the rine of Pine-nuts, leaves of Myrtle, Maidenhair, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, burn them to aſhes; to which adde Labdanum powder'd, Myrrhe, each e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts; Oyl of Raddiſh-ſeeds, old wine, each as much as is ſufficient, make an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum ſteeped in wine and powder'd Oyl of Myrtles, each one part, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of binding Bean-tree, Lab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danum, each three drams, Oyl of Myrtles, Wine, each half an ounce, mix them to an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="63" facs="tcp:119632:40"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gauls, Indian Myrobalanes, leaves of Myrtles, each equal parts, boyl them in Wine, ſtrein them, and boyl it again to a thickneſs, then add Labdanum, Maſtick, each one ounce, oyl of unripe Olives, water, each one pint, boyl them again to a thickneſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e ounces, Gaules, Myrrhe, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, each one dram, wilde Carduus two drams, diſſolve them all in oyl of Roſes, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the Juice of Myrtle-leaves, the Juice of wilde Olives, each two ounces, dried Roſes half an ounce, Romane Wormwood two drams, Vineger half a pint, boyl them together till one half be conſumed, ſtrein it, and add Labdanum two ounces; to all which well bruiſed, adde Oyl of Myrtles, Juice of ſowr Grapes, as much as will ſuffice to make it thick as honey, Maidenhair powder'd three drams, Gallia Moſchata one dram or two, and make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrtle-berries, the rine of Reeds burnt, the rine of Pine-nuts burnt, each half an ounce; leaves of Myrtles, Wormwood, each two drams, powder and mix them with
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:119632:41"/>Oyl of Myrtles to the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maidenhair burnt, Myrtle-leaves, the rine of Pine burnt, each equal parts; Frankincenſe, Labdanum alike, powder them and mix them with the oyl of Raddiſh-ſeeds and Wine, into the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ointments to reſtore the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Cleopatra's <hi>Ointment to ingender Hair.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>WHen you have bruiſed the roots of tender Reeds, preſs forth the Juice and mix dried Flies with it into a pulſtiſe, and when you have wrought it together and mixt it with Bears fat and oyl of Cedars, uſe it to anoint with; but to take away the ſmell of it, pour ſome wine to it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Another of</hi> Cleopatra's.</head>
                  <p>Burn dried Flax ſeed together with the ſtubble of Flax, and being powder'd, lay it on with oyl of Turky-millet.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Lay upon the Hair burnt Bees mixt with Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to make the hair grow again.</head>
                  <p>Take oyl of Juniper, oyl of Nuts, each one ounce, white honey, juice of Dock, each half an ounce, Smallage-ſeeds, Aſarabacca pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd,
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:119632:41"/>each two ounces, incorporate them and anoint the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the rougheſt foam of the Sea burnt, and powder'd and ſmoothed with oyl, lay it on the place, but eſpecially let it be Lamp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>The ſhells of Sea Hedge-hogs burnt, and wrought together with Bears-greaſe, lay up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the places, being firſt rubbed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Reeds burnt, mix them with Bears-greaſe, and lay it on the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of <hi>Oreſtinus</hi> againſt an old Baldneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take of Mouſeturd, Frankincenſe, each two ounces, diſſolve them in the ſharpeſt Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and anoint the place, firſt ſhaved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sea-Hedge-hogs burnt together with their ſhells, unripe Gauls, bitter Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds burnt, each two ounces, Mouſeturd one dram, powder them well and diſſolve them in vineger, and lay them on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the hairs of a Bear burnt, Maidenhair burnt, the roots of Reeds burnt, the leaves of Miſſletoe burnt, ſhreds of Hair-cloth burnt, each equal parts, mix it up with
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:119632:42"/>Bears-greaſe and Rozen of Cedar-tree.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of <hi>Ortho</hi> the Sicilian.</head>
                  <p>Take of the aſhes of the leaſt Frogs burnt in an earthen pot, one part; Mouſeturd, white Hellebore, the roots of Reeds burnt, white pepper, each alike parts, mix them with vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and apply them to the place firſt rubb'd and ſhaved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the aſhes of Goats hoofs burnt, the Juice of Thapſia, the foam of the Sea, Mouſeturd, the ſcum of Niter, Myrrhe, white Pepper, Ginger, each alike parts, powder them well and mix them up with Goats gaul.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of the leaves of Sallow, the Juice of Myrtle leaves, each half an ounce, Labdanum one ounce, Oyl of Myrtles as much as will ſuffice to make it into an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent, mix them and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bees burnt, Maidenhair burnt, Oyl of Roſes, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to make hairs grow on thoſe troubled with an Elephantiaſis.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of a Moul, of Waſps, of Hens, each two drams, Oyl of Flower-de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luce two ounces; Labdanum one ounce and
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:119632:42"/>a half, a little Wax, and make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to produce hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the rine of Reeds, ſcum of Niter, each half an ounce, mix them up with Tar, and uſe it, but you muſt daily ſcrape the place, and rub it with a Cloth; for ſo it will cauſe the hair very quickly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Houſe-mice burnt one part; ſhreds of flaxen-cloth burnt one part, rine of Reeds one part, theſe being all dried, powder them, and mixing them with honey, reduce them to the conſiſtence of it, and then adde mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and fat melted, and put them in a braſs Box, &amp; rub the bald place till the hair comes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Poppy, leaves of Myrtle, Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair, Lavender, Cyperus, Smallage-ſeeds, Emblick, Myrobalanes, Cypreſs-nuts, each one dram, water three pints, boyl them all till two pints be waſted, ſtrein it, and adde Oyl of Myrtles one pound, boyl them again till the water be conſumed, and adde the rines of Pine-nuts, Labdanum, each one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the head or hide of an Earth-Hedge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hog burnt, powder it and work it up with ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and anoint the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="68" facs="tcp:119632:43"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Burn together a Sea-horſe and a little Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, mix them up with Gooſe-greaſe, and the place being prepared with Niter, anoint it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sword-flag a ſufficient quantity, burn the leaves in a pot, then mix it up with Rozen and Pine-aſhes, ſcarifie the bald place and lay it on, and binde it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>
                     <hi>Another of</hi> Soranus.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bears-greaſe, the aſhes of Reed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leaves burnt, the powder of Braſs, each one part, Vineger, old Oyl, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of Reed burnt, the hairs of a Bear, Maidenhair, Bears-greaſe, Tar, Goats hairs burnt, Rozen of Cedar, each alike parts, mix them together, and anoint the place rub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the leaves of Greek-reed burnt, half an ounce, Mouſeturd two drams, Hedge-hogs burnt one dram, powder them, mix them with Vineger, lay it on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Baldneſs.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bulls fat ſunned one pound, the froth that cleaveth to Canes, one ounce, the juice of Thapſia an ounce and a half, Myrrhe
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:119632:43"/>one ounce, Maidenhair one pound, an Aſſes member, an Aſſes ſpleen, Labdanum, each one pound, ſteep the Labdanum in a little wine, and melt the fat with the ſteem of water, burn the Aſſes member and ſhave it, but burn the Spleen in a new pot with Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair, and powder and ſearce what ought to be, then make them with new wine, and uſe it before bathing, the head being firſt comb'd.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An approved Ointment to cauſe a Beard.</head>
                  <p>Take of Oyl of ſweet Almonds, Myrrhe, each an ounce, the rine of the roots of Reeds burnt, Maidenhair burnt, each two drams, heads of Flies burnt, Bees bruiſed in their emptineſs, each half a dram, Labdanum two drams, Honey one ounce, powder them, and with a little Wax, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of a Mole dried in an oven, two ounces, the aſhes of Bees, of Filberds burnt, each one dram and a half, Mouſeturd two drams, Labdanum a dram and a half, the beſt Honey one ounce, Oyl of Nard, Wax, each a ſufficient quantity; make a Liniment, but in the morning following you muſt waſh your face with this Decoction: Take of Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denhair, male Southernwood, Roſemary, Myrtle-leaves, the rine of Reed roots<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Flow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of Chamemel, red Roſes, leaves of ſowre
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:119632:44"/>Dock, each one handful, Pockwood half a pound, make a Decoction and uſe it as hath been ſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fenigreek ſix pints, Flax-ſeed three pints, Labdanum eight ounces, the Juice of binding Bean-tree two ounces, of the Indian leaf two ounces, twenty Gauls, Aromatical Onyx two ounces, Syrian Cane two ounces and a half, Bdellium two ounces, Myrtle burnt twenty four ounces, Musk three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Florence Flower-de-luce two ounces, powder them ſeverally, ſearce them and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to cauſe Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of Graſhoppers burnt, of Bees burnt, Oyl of Myrtles or fat, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments that hinder the growth of hair.</head>
                  <p>Take the Decoction of Spurge mixt with Vineger, unſlaked Lime and Mallows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gum of Ivy, Ants Eggs, yellow Arſnick, Colophony, each one ounce, Leeches burnt half an ounce, powder them and mix them with the blood of Frogs, and make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the blood of Bats, the Juice of Ivy,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:119632:44"/>the Juice of Radiſh, Goats Suet, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix them and make an oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the fat of Frogs, of a Mole, a Bat, Gum of Ivy, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Opium, Henbane, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, powder them, and with Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger bring them into the form of an Unguent, with which anoint the hairs daily.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of Caſtor, ſcum'd Honey enough to make it into an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a whole Hedge-hog, boyl it in oyl till the fleſh be parted from the bones, ſtrein it, and with the aforeſaid oyl mix Ants Eggs, and anoint it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Hemlock-ſeed a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, powder them, and with the blood of a Bat, bring them to the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gum of Ivy one ounce, yellow Arſnick, Colophony, Hemlock-ſeed, each half an ounce, Caſtor two drams, Opium one dram, Henbane one dram and a half; Juice of Hemlock, the blood of a Bat, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:119632:45"/>quantity, make an Ointment to an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the bare places.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the blood of a Bat, of mans blood, new Caſſia, each alike parts, Ants Eggs, Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane-ſeed, black Poppy-ſeed, each alike parts, pouder what is fit, and mix with the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cimolian earth, Ceruſſe, each one part, Roche-alume half a part, juice of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Tartar pouder'd, ſcum'd Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and anoint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gum of white Vine, Gum of Ivy, Bryony, pouder them and mix them with oyl into the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ants Eggs, the blood of Frogs, the ruſt of Iron, mix them up with ſpittle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gaul of a Hedge-hog, the Gaul of a Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>morant, Sea-ſhells burnt and pouder'd, the blood of a Bat, each a ſufficient quantity; make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of Swallows burnt, the milk of Spurge, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:119632:45"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gum-arabick, Tragacanth, burnt Braſs, Verdigreaſe, Arſnick, Long-pepper, white, black Pepper, Blood-ſtone, Starch-corn, Dyers Madder, Scales of Braſs burnt, each two drams, Dragons blood, Juice of binding Bean-tree, each a dram and a half, Frankincenſe, Spike, burnt Gauls, each one dram, Sarcocol, Ammoniacum, diſſolved in Aquavitae, each half an ounce, pouder them and mix them with the Juice of Citrons or Lemmons, and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Henbane, Dragons blood, Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arabick, white Frankincenſe, each ſix drams, Night-ſhade water a ſufficient quantity, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them and mix them to the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Dates two drams, Spike one dram and a half, pouder and mix them with Honey, and the turd of a Mole, to the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ruſt of Iron, Sea-ſhells burnt, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them with faſting ſpittle.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to make the Hair ſhed, and grow no more.</head>
                  <p>Take of yellow Arſnick, Ants Eggs, Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arabick,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:119632:46"/>each half an ounce, Gum of Ivy two ounces; with the blood of a Bat, or Juice of Henbane, make an Unguent, apply it, the hairs being firſt cut.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments that take away the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of gold coloured Arſnick, ſeven or ten ſcruples, unſlaked Lime the ſame quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, Starch-corn two ounces, Selinuſian earth an ounce, powder them and fine ſearſe them; when you would uſe it, take a ſufficient quantity and ſhake it together with water, then lay it on, and ſee that it burn not.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take two parts of unſlaked Lime, yellow Arſnick, one part, put them into a leaden morter, and powder them with water or the juice of Ptiſan poured to them, and when they are black, command them to be laid on hot, eſpecially in a Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sandarach one dram, unſlaked Lime, eighteen ounces, pounder them and boyl them carefully with water, and when they begin to boyl, take it off and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Starch-corn, unſlaked Lime, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Arſnick, each one ounce, pouder, ſearſe them and lay them by, and uſe them as hath been ſaid.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:119632:46"/>
                  <head>Another that preſently takes away the hair by the roots.</head>
                  <p>Take of unſlaked Lime, Cimolian earth, a burnt Pummy-ſtone, each eighteen ounces, yellow Arſnick three ounces, pouder them and lay them by; when you have occaſion to uſe them, dilute them with water, and ſo uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to take away the Hair, and thin the Skin.</head>
                  <p>Take the juice of the leaves of wilde Cow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumber, milk of Almonds, unſlaked Lime, yellow Arſnick, Galbanum ſteept in Wine, and ſtreined, each a ſufficient quantity; when they are boyled, adde to them Oyl of Roſes, Maſtick, each a ſufficient quantity; Frankin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, the Gumm of Juniper-tree, Roſes, Cloves, Cummin, Nutmeg, Cynamon, each a little, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of the aſhes of Maſt-tree, two parts, yellow Arſnick one part, boyl them in Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of black Soap one pound, Tartar, one ounce and a half, yellow Arſnick ſix oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, juice of Cyperus fifteen drams, unſlaked Lime half an ounce, capital Lees one ounce, put the Lime in the Lees, ſtrein it, and mix it with the reſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:119632:47"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Gum of Ivy two ounces, yellow Arſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nick, Ants Eggs, Gum-arabick, each three drams, pouder them and mix them with ſtrong Vineger.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of yellow Arſnick three ounces, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaked Lime one dram, ſtrong Lye a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, boyl them till the feathers come off, a quill dipt in it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to take hair off the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Colophony two ounces, Maſtick, Ammoniacum cleanſed, each one ounce, diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve them in a clean earthen veſſel, and ſtre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n it upon cold water, take it and work it together, and diſſolve a little of it over the fire, and apply it warm, letting it lye on for two hours, and then take it away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to take away the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of the powder of an Owl one ounce, Cummin, the blood of a Bat, each three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Musk one ſcruple, make a Liniment: we muſt have a ſpecial care that the part to which the Ointment muſt be applied, be firſt waſhed with the Lye made of Vine aſhes, and if an itching be left in the part after applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Medicine, anoint it with Rhaſes, white Ointment, or with the Decoction of Henbane-ſeeds, or of Colewort-ſeeds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:119632:47"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the blood of a Tortoiſe, of Frogs, of a Bat, Ants Eggs, red Ar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nick, Gum of Ivy, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them with Vineger, and anoint it diſcreetly, that it do not excoriate.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of yellow Arſnick, Juice of Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bane, each alike parts, mix them and anoint the part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to take away hairs from any part of the Body.</head>
                  <p>Take three whites of Eggs bruiſed, unſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Lime eight ounces, yellow Arſnick one ounce, a ſufficient quantity of Lye, make an Unguent, with which beſmearing a feather, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noint the hairy parts, but when they have been anointed a quarter of an hour, waſh off the Unguent with warm water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ants Eggs, Juice of Henbane, Hemlock, ſeeds of Fleawort, the blood of a Bat, of a Tortoiſe, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and anoint the place: others run over the place with a plate of Gold red hot, ſo that no Doun any more appear.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:119632:48"/>
               <head>Of Ointments that colour the Hair.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Hair yellow.</head>
                  <p>RAw Lupines laid on with water and Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, do make the Hair yellow.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the middle Bark of Elder, Flowers of Broom, Saffron, yelks of Eggs, each a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity, boyl them in water, and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that which ſwims a top, and ſo anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Tartar burnt, Oyl of Acorns, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent, with which anoint the haires in the ſun, by combing.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe one ounce, white Salt half an ounce, pouder and mix them with Oyl of Acorns into the form of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Flowers of Mullein one handful, Fenigreek two ounces, Vine aſhes, and of the wood of Ivy, each one handful, ten pints of water, boyl them all till one half be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed, ſtrein it, and add of the whiteſt Soap three pound, Saffron two drams, leave them ſo in the ſun for a moneth, mixing them eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day with a ſtick; with this anoint the hairs in the ſun.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="79" facs="tcp:119632:48"/>
                  <head>A Liniment to clarifie and whiten the Hair.</head>
                  <p>Take of Swallows dung, the roots of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane, Radiſh-ſeeds, Brimſtone, flowers of Capers, Frankincenſe, each half an ounce, incorporate them all together with the like quantity of the Gaul or a white Ox; rub the hairs with it, being firſt waſht with the Lye of Vines, and dried, and while the haires are dried of their own accord after the Lotion, rubbing them, waſh them again in the ſame Lye, and dry them by degrees with a hot cloth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments that dye the hair black.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſcum of ſilver, Limolian earth, liquid Alume, each alike parts, the haires being firſt waſht and dried, anoint them over night, and binde over them Beets leaves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Selinuſian earth, ſcum of ſilver, Lime, each alike parts, reduce them with wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to the thickneſs of Honey, and when you have firſt waſht the hairs with a Lye, then anoint them; and likewiſe laying on the leaves of Beets, binde them up, and in the morning comb them out.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Ano<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>her to black the Beard.</head>
                  <p>Dried and burnt Lead mixt with the juice of crude Beets, to the thickneſs of Honey,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:119632:49"/>laid on, and let alone till dinner time, then waſht off.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gauls, Frankincenſe, Gith, each two drams, pouder them and put them in a Quince hollowed, cloſe it up, and wrap it in Bread-paſte, and bake it in an oven, till it is burnt, pouder it and mix the aſhes with oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gauls burnt with common oyl, two ounces, Roche-alume two drams, ſalt Gem one dram, with Oyl of Coſtmary make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Liniment that will make gray Hairs black.</head>
                  <p>Take of Black, Emblick, Myrobalanes, Gauls, each twenty, Labdanum a ſufficient quantity, Leaves and Berries of Myrtle, each threeſcore, pouder and ſearſe them, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſe them in three pints of Oyl for three days, then boyl them till they grow thick, and anoint the roots of the hair with it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the droſs of Iron, filing of Lead, each a ſufficient quantity, boyl them in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger till one half be conſumed, ſtrein it an anoint the parts: an unction of burnt Lead made with the juice of Beets to the conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of honey, will make the Beard black.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:119632:49"/>
                  <head>Of Ointments that dy the hair white.</head>
                  <p>Take of Swallows dung, the Gaul of a Bull, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Elecampane, the rine of Radiſh-root, Alume, Glew, each one part, mix them and anoint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Swallowes dung, Radiſh-ſeed, Brimſtone, the bark of Caper-roots, a Cows Gaul, the beſt Vineger, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to colour the hair red.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Tartar pouder'd, Oyl of wilde Cucumber, each a ſufficient quantity, make a Liniment to anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments to curl the hair.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of Rams horns, cut it and pouder it with Oyl, and anoint the hair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the root of Danewort, and pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it with Oyl, then anoint the head, and binde leaves of the ſame over it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the juice of Beets, of Myrtles, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Oyl, each a ſufficient quantity, mix and anoint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:119632:50"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Pine-kernels burnt and pouder'd, Oyl of Myrtles, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the ſcum of Salt, which is gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in boyling, Myrrhe pouder'd, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe, Gum-arabick, Oyl of Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nigreek, Oyl of Henbane, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Ointment for the hair.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ointments to take away the faults of the Eye-brows.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For the falling of the hair off the Eye-brows.</head>
                  <p>TAke of the filings of Lead, of Drakes fat, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Filberds roſted and pouder'd, the fat of a Goat or Bear, each a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, mix them to an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="83" facs="tcp:119632:50"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of black Henbane two drams, Maidenhair one dram Ointment of Flower-de-luce three ſpoonfuls, pouder and mix them to the form of an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to make the hair of the Eye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brows grow again.</head>
                  <p>Take of Henbane-ſeed burnt, a ſufficient quantity, with water make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bees burnt and pounder'd, a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity, and with Oyl make a Lini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for the Eye-brows.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Lice in the Eye-brows.</head>
                  <p>Take the yelk of an Egg boyled hard, a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle Aloes, mix them and anoint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Quickſilver killed with ſpittle, Stavesacer, each half an ounce, butter a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take one Apple roaſted and cleanſed, Quickſilver killed with ſpittle, a ſufficient quantity, mix them well and anoint.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Stavesacer one ounce, Oyl of Wormwood two ounces, Wax a ſufficient quantity, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:119632:51"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sugar'd-alume, Aloes, Staveſacer, Vineger of Squills, each a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments that take away the black and blewneſs of the Eye-lids and Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Beans husked and pouder'd, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, Honey what is convenient, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of yelks of Eggs boyled hard, Honey what is convenient, and beat them together to the form of an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with which anoint the parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ceruſſe, Cummin, Bean, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, pouder them, and with the juice of Coriander make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for the ſhedding of the hairs of the Eye-lids.</head>
                  <p>Take of Stibium burnt, and quencht in womans milk thirteen drams, Aloes, Myrrhe, Spikenard, each two drams, burnt Barley half an ounce, pouder them and mix them with a ſufficient quantity of water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="85" facs="tcp:119632:51"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Marrow of the right leg of an Ox, of Sut, each a ſufficient quantity, and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For the ſhedding of the Eye-brows and Beard.</head>
                  <p>Take of Henbane two drams, Mouſeturd one dram, Maidenhair two drams, Oyl of Flower-de-luce a ſufficient quantity, pouder and mix them with the Oyl, foment the part and then anoint it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for dropping of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe, Cummin, Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Ammoniacum, Bolearmenick, each half an ounce, Saffron 2 drams, pouder them all and mix them with the whites of Eggs, and lay them on the forehead and tempels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Frankincenſe, Maſtick, Gum-ara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bick, Tragacanth, Bolearmenick, Tutty, Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gons blood, each half an ounce, pouder and mix them with the whites of Eggs, and apply them to to the forehead and tempels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Ointments to ſtop droppings of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Celandine, Rue, Vervin, the bark of Fennel-roots, each one handful, bruiſe them, and make a paſte with old Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe, which boyl in white Wine till the wine be almoſt conſumed, ſtrein it, and adde
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:119632:52"/>new white Wax, Aloes, each three drams; Verdegreaſe, Saffron, each one dram, Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incenſe three drams, Maſtick four drams, Camphure one dram, make an Ointment to anoint the eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aloes, Sarcocol, Frankincenſe, each a ſufficient quantity, pouden and mix them with the Juice of Fennel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for tears of the Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tutty prepared Sarcocol, Myrrhe, Frankincenſe, Styrax-calamite, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, each one ſcruple; dried Roſes, Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mach, Dragons blood, each ſix drams, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them, and with the mucilage of Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragacan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>n and Arabick make an Ointment, of which put a little in the eyes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for red Eyes.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cummin poude<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>'d, a ſufficient quantity, mix it with Wax, and lay it on the eyes when they are aſleep.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tragacanth, Gum-arabick, Roſes pouder'd, Starch-corn, Ceruſſe, each two ounces, Opium one ſcruple, pouder them and mix them with womans milk.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:119632:52"/>
               <head>Of Ointments that cure the faults of the skin of the Head.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For Running-ſores of the Head.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Ceruſſe ſix drams, ſcum of Silver half a dram, Brimſtone ſix drams, Oyl of Roſes or Myrtles, Wax a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſcum of Silver one dram, tender leaves of Rue, five and twenty drams, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, Oyl of Roſes or Myrtles, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, mix them and anoint with a feather.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uſſe, Rue, Manna, Frankincenſe, each a hundred drams, Bark of Pine-tree fifty drams, Oyl of Myrtles three pints, and as much Vineger, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of the filings of Lead, Vine-branches, Frankincenſe, Myrrhe, ſcum of Niter, each fifty drams, Oyl of Myrtles, Vineger as much as is ſufficient, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment of Queen <hi>Cleopatra</hi>'s for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of rub'd Ceruſſe, Frankincenſe, each
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:119632:53"/>two drams, brimſtone one dram, powder them and with Oyl lay them on.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Sores and Dander.</head>
                  <p>Take of Niter Copperas, each one dram, Oyl a ſufficient quantity, powder and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of Cleopatra's.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Sulphur ſix drams, male Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kincenſe, cleft Allom, wilde Staveſacer, rock<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et, ſcum of Niter, Copperas, each one dram, three forigs of Rue, Oyl of Bayes or Myrtels, Vineger, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Sulphur, ſcum of Silver, Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſſe, each alike part, Saffron half ſo much, powder them and uſe them with Candy wine.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take ſcum of Silver, unſlaked Lime, each twenty five drams, Vinegar or Oyl, three parts of a pint, powder and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Copperas two drams, Sandarach half an ounce, ſcum of Silver one dram, Oyl of Myrtels, Vinegar, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Sores and Worms.</head>
                  <p>Take of juice of Beets, of Celandine, Hogs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe, each two ounces, white Hellebore
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:119632:53"/>two ounces two drams, mix them and make an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Worms and Scabs.</head>
                  <p>Take of white and black Hellebore, live Sulphure, yellow Arſnick, Litharge, unſlaked Lime, Vitriol, Alume, Gauls, Sut, each half an ounce, Quick-ſilver killed, Verdegreaſe, each two drams, juice of Fumitory, Oyl, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Worms.</head>
                  <p>Take of Fenigreek one pound, Dragons blood pouder'd, one ounce, Pummy-ſtone one pound, Turpentine five ounces, Honey one ounce, four yelks of Eggs, Oyl of Roſes two ounces, mix them and make an Unguent; which uſe, the head being firſt ſhaved, and waſht with a childes urine, and cleanſed with a ſpunge, and anointed over with Oyl of Flax-ſeed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Celandine three parts, Sowes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greaſe as much, white Hellebore one part, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for ſcurf in childrens Heads.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe, Orrice-root, black Helle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bore, Oyl of Eggs, each a ſufficient quantity, powder them and mix them into the form of an Unguent, alſo Oyl of Bread-corn is good.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:119632:54"/>
                  <head>For Dander in the Head.</head>
                  <p>Take flour of Vetches, Fenigreek, Niter, Bran, Myrtles, Muſtard-ſeed, each fifteen drams, common Oyl<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as much as is ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent, Vineger, Water, each a little, make an Unguent, with which anoint the head, firſt waſht and ſhaved.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take ſcum of Niter, Copperas, each alike parts, wine a ſufficient quantity, mix them &amp; rub the head three o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> four times a moneth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> of Wine, a Pummy ſtone, Niter, Lupines, each one part, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Cimolian earth, the Gaul of an Ox or Sow, Vineger, each a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Lice.</head>
                  <p>Take of Stavesacer two parts, Sandarach, Niter, each one part; Oyl, Vineger each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Hellebore, Stavesacer, Niter, each alike parts; Oyl a ſufficient quantity, mix them, and apply them in a Bath.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Lice and Nits.</head>
                  <p>Take of Stavesacer, Quickſilver killed
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:119632:54"/>with ſpittle, each three drams, common Oyl three ounces, Wax one ounce, make an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent, with which anoint the head in ſtead of Soap, when it is waſht.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sandarach, Niter, each one dram, Stavesacer two drams; Oyl, Vineger, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Bays, Radiſh-ſeeds, each two drams; Pepper, Saffron, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for red Specks in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Dock, Sows-greaſe, each two ounces, white wax one ounce, melt them and adde Quickſilver kill'd, Camphure, each a little; Juice of Wormwood, Honey, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for a red face.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Sulphur, yellow Arſnick, Turky Soap, each half a dram, Sut two drams, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of ſeven Oranges, Juice of Night-ſhade, water of Water-lillies, Snail-water, each two drams, white Wax half an ounce, the fat of a Hen, and a Ram, each one ounce and a half, the green roots of <gap reason="blank" extent="1 word">
                        <desc> _____ </desc>
                     </gap> two drams, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:119632:55"/>
                  <head>An Ointment for Wrinckles and Pimples of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Mix the Gaul of a Goat with the flour of Lupines, and at night rub the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of white Curral half an ounce, ſalt Gem, Ceruſſe, Camphure, each two drams, white Wax one dram, Roſe-water an ounce, the fat of a Hen waſht, two ounces, pouder and mix them for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Pimples.</head>
                  <p>Take of white wax one pound, oyl of violets one ounce, Quickſilver half an ounce, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick one dram and a half, a little Camphure, Litharge one dram, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Biles or Botches.</head>
                  <p>Take the flour of Lupines, Beans, white Vetches, everlaſting Peaſe, each two drams, flour of Barley, of Lentils, each one dram, Radiſh-ſeed, Tragacanth, Starch-corn, each half a dram; Melon-ſeeds husked three drams, Saffron half a ſcruple, pouder them and work them with womans milk, at night anoint the face, and in the morning waſh it with the water of the rines of Melons and Violets.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="93" facs="tcp:119632:55"/>
                  <head>An Ointment that takes away all Bunchings and Speckles of tho Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of the roots of Aſs-cowcumber, white Been, Bryony, Lupines, each half an ounce, Ceruſſe, Litharge, Tartar, each one dram; Cane-roots, Serapine, Pigeons dung, each two ſcruples, Oyl of Turky-millet three ounces, Oyl of Juniper, Oyl of Bread-corn, each two ounces and a half; Juice of Oren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges four ounces, pouder what is to be pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd, and fine ſearſe them, then boyl them all till the Juice is conſumed, then take them from the fire, alwayes ſtirring them with a ſpattle till they are cold, then add the white of one new laid Egg beaten and ſtreined; Camphure pouder'd one dram, always mix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing them, then waſh it in one pint of water, preſt from yong Canes, waſhing it ten times in that water, and ſtirring it with a ſpattle, and it is excellent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For Botches and Worms of the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Hens fat, Betony, each as much as is ſufficient, mix them and beat them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to whiten Skars.</head>
                  <p>Take of Oyl of Tartar, ſeeds of Fleawort, each one ounce, infuſe them in the mucilage of Borax, or ſalt Gem diſſolved in Oyl of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, an ounce.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="94" facs="tcp:119632:56"/>
                  <head>A Liniment for high red Skars.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Litharge two drams, Oyl of Tartar, Balſom of Saturn, each one dram, camphure one ſcruple, Spermacety one dram, Oyl of Eggs two ounces, mix them and make a liniment, uſe it four times a day; the rich<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er ſort may uſe Oyl of Talc, which is moſt excellent for all blemiſhes.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to take away the thickneſs of the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh Butter, Turpentine, each one ounce, Lilly roots roaſted in the leaves of Beets under the aſhes, three ounces unſlaked Lime five times waſht in Roſe-water, or the juice of Balm, freſh Hogs-greaſe melted in Roſe-water, each one ounce, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the tenderer ſort.</head>
                  <p>Take of Lilly roots roſted under the aſhes one pound, bruiſe them in a morter, to which adde Sugar-Candy three ounces, make an Ointment to apply to the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Warts in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Athenian Honey, the ſharpeſt Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>negar, each twelve drams, mix them carefully and anoint them, rubbing them with the fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="95" facs="tcp:119632:56"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſcum of Quickſilver three drams, pure Turpentine the quantity of an Egyptian bean, a little Oyl; mix them, and when you have cleanſed the face, take a little on your finger, then bruiſe it well, and anoint them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Allom cut and well pouder'd, Turpentine, each as much as it ſufficient, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Indian Coſtus bruiſed and ſearſed, a Goats Gaul, each a ſufficient quantity, make an ointment, with which anoint them towards night, and in the morning waſh the face with milk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Ringworms in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Vineger of Squills two ounces, Aloes, the Juice of ſowre Dock, Oyl of Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar, each three drams, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the diſtilled water of ſowr Dock four ounces, Borax three drams, common Salt one dram, Vineger of Squills one ounce, mix them, and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Dock-roots three ounces, roaſt them under the aſhes, afterwards with Vineger
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:119632:57"/>of Squills make a Liniment; if this cure not, adde of Quickſilver half a dram, or Subli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mate one ſcruple; waſh the face often with the water of Myrtles, or of Roſe-ſeeds, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards adde alſo a little white of an Egg, that the skin may reſiſt it the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tartar two drams, pouder it and apply it with the whites of Eggs, or with three drams of burnt Alume do the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for callous Warts.</head>
                  <p>Take of French Soap half an ounce, Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniacum, Styrax, Frankincenſe, each one dram, diſſolve them in water and make it to the thickneſs of a Cerot, then anoint with it, and after one hour, waſh it off with warm water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Niter, Hyſſope, Pennyroyal, Salt digged up, each equal parts, beat them and ſearſe them, make it up with Cerot of Roſes, and uſe it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of Baſtil, red Niter, green Pennyroyal, cleft Alume, Indian Coſtus, each alike parts, pouder and ſearſe them, and mix them with a ſufficient quantity of Goat, or Hens-greaſe, to the form of an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:119632:57"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of burnt Salt, Pennyroyal, Hyſſope, Ammoniacum, Sumach, each equal parts, oyl of Roſes as much as is ſufficient, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Ringworms of the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Aloes two drams, diſſolve it in Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger of Squills to the form of a Liniment, anoint the parts affected at night.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Bryony, as many as are ſufficient, work them up with ſalt in the ſhar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſt Vineger, and apply it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another approved one.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſharp Dock two parts, Gentian one part, boyl them in water, then ſtrein them, and mixing it with Calves-greaſe, boyl it again with a ſlow fire, to the conſiſtence of an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Surn-burns, Clefts of the Lips, and Speckles in the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take twenty Snailes with their ſhells, bruiſe them, then adde the weight of them in Ceruſſe, new Wax three ounces, Harts<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horn one ounce, make a Liniment, then waſh the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="98" facs="tcp:119632:58"/>
                  <head>An Ointment for Warts in the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Aſarabacca, temper them in Roſe-water two dayes, bake them and anoint the part.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Celandine, as much as is ſufficient pouder'd, mixt with greaſe and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied, it waſtes and takes them away.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For a red Face.</head>
                  <p>Take Brimſtone one ounce, Ceruſſe waſht two drams, Juice of Lemmons one ounce, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply it at night with the Decoction of Bran.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Tartar, Oyl of Roſes, Juice of ſowr Dock, of Bays, of Graſs-plantane, each four ounces, Ceruſſe one ounce and a half, Litharge of Gold two drams, Quickſilver killed one ounce and a half, roots of Aſpho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del burnt under the aſhes two ounces, make a Liniment in a leaden morter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Citrine ointment half a pound, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge four ounces, Ceruſſe waſht two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Cotton, Alume burnt, Tartar calcined, each one ounce and a half, the Juice of Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>campane roots, the Juice of ſowr Dock, Sows<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bread, Lemons, each five ounces, Camphure three drams, oyl of Roſes a pound and a half, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="99" facs="tcp:119632:58"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Juice of Fumitory, Plantane, Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rel, each three ounces, Oyl of Roſes one ounce, Gum-tragacanth, Arabick, each half a dram, Dragons blood two drams, new Wax as much as is ſufficient, make an Ointment to uſe going to bed, and the next day waſh with the Decoction of Beans.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge twice or thrice infuſed in Vineger, one ounce, nouriſh it with white Wine and Goard-ſeed, and ſtir it till it be brought to the form of an Unguent, adde of Camphure diſſolved in Roſe-water half an ounce, anoint the face, and in the morn waſh it with the Decoction of Beans.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Liniment for a ſcabby face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge of Gold one ounce and a half, Ceruſſe waſht in Plantane-water, and Horſe-tail two ounces, Oyl of Roſes three ounces, boyl the Oyl, and with white Wax make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For redneſs and bunchings in the face.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes, Oyl of Tartar, each four ounces, juice of Wood-ſorrel three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Ceruſſe waſht one dram and a half, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge of Gold two ounces, Quickſilver kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one ounce and a half, roots of Aſphodel
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:119632:59"/>burnt under the aſhes, make a Liniment in a leaden morter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For leprous Faces.</head>
                  <p>Take the powders of Citrine-ungent, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge of Gold, each four ounces, Ceruſſe waſht two ounces, Borax, Alume burnt, Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar calcined, each one ounce and a half, the juice of Elecampane-roots, of ſowre Dock, Sows-bread, Lemmons, each five ounces, oyl of Roſes one pound, Quickſilver kill'd with ſpittle four ounces; make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of the root of Birthwort, Graſs-plantane the fine taken off and waſht nine days in ſpring-water, then ſearſe it all, and take what you pleaſe, and diſſolve it in Plantane, or Purſlane-water, and anoint the face.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Knobs appearing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Skin.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of Saffron, mix them with womans milk, and apply it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Surn-burns.</head>
                  <p>Take Juice of Plantane, Night-ſhade, each one dram and a half, Litharge of Gold, of Silver, each one dram, burnt Lead an ounce, Tutty prepared ſix drams, Camphure half a dram, oyl of Roſes, Wax, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="101" facs="tcp:119632:59"/>
                  <head>An Ointments for Ringworms.</head>
                  <p>Take of Vitriol, Frankincenſe, Myrrhe, cleft Alume, each one ounce; Aloes, live Sulphur, each half an ounce, make it up with wine to a convenient thickneſs, and twice or thrice a day anoint the parts firſt rubbed.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Vitriol half an ounce, Juice of bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Bean-tree two drams, ſcales of Braſs half an ounce, live Sulphur ſix drams, white Vitriol, Gum each one ounce, Vineger, as much as is ſufficient, in which when you have diſſolv'd the Gum and mixt the other things, adde the Lees of Oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Brimſtone, Frankincenſe, Myrrhe; Copperas, raw Vitriol, each two drams, Gum half an ounce; Vineger, Oyl of Cedar, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Gum of Ethiopian-olive, five and twenty drams, Gum forty drams, Cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peras ſixteen drams, live Brimſtone, Frank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>incenſe, ruſt of Braſs, the Juice of binding Bean-tree, white Myrrhe, each ten drams, Vineger as much as is ſufficient, when they
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:119632:60"/>are all diſſolved, mix them up with thick Lees of Oyl.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for old Tetters.</head>
                  <p>Take of Copperas, Fenigreek mollified, Cardamoms, each two drams, Gith, Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree leaves, each one dram and a half, the ſharpeſt Vineger, as much as is ſufficient, powder them, and bring them to the thick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Burns.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes, Roſe-water, whites of Eggs, each a ſufficient quantity; mix them, and for four days apply them to the burnt place, the fifth day lay on the following pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter: Take of Oyl of Nuts, new Wax, each one ounce, melt them together.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Scalds and Burns.</head>
                  <p>Take of the middle barke of Elder, ſix drams, Oyl of Roſes one ounce and a half, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, each half a dram, white Wax, two ounces, boyl them in four pints of water till one half be waſted, ſcum'd, and cooled, that which ſwims a top is fit to apply to the burn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for a Burn.</head>
                  <p>Take of the juice of Night-ſhade, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, each two ounces, the middle bark of Elder, Oyl, each one ounce, boyl them in a
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:119632:60"/>double veſſel till the juices be waſted, then add Ceruſſe waſht in Roſe-water, Litharge of Gold, each a dram and a half, Tutty prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, three drams; the bark of Frankincenſe two drams, freſh Hogs-greaſe w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſht in Roſe-water, ten drams, white Wax as much as is ſufficient, make a Liniment; towards the end adde three whites of Eggs, Camphure half a dram.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of new Lime waſht in Roſe-water, three pound, Juice of Roſes, Juice of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, each two pound, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes two ounces, Oyl preſt from Goard-ſeeds, one ounce and a half, white Wax as much as is ſufficient, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to ſmooth the Face af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter a Burn.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pomatum, Oyl of Roſes, each four ounces, ointment of Roſes two ounces, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pomatum four ounces, Oyl of Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes three ounces, Citrine ointment half an ounce, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="104" facs="tcp:119632:61"/>
                  <head>Another for Burns and Scalds.</head>
                  <p>Take old Lard, and put it upon a red hot iron, then receive the hot drops falling into cold water, and take the fat which ſwims a top, and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>k it with Roſe-water, and lay it on the Burn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for a Scald.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ceruſſe waſht in Roſe-water, one ounce, Lime waſht in Roſe-water, three drams, the powder of Citrine Ointment half an ounce, the mucilage of the ſeeds of Quin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and Peares extracted with Roſe-water, three ounces, beat them all in a morter to the form of a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to take away the marks of the Small-pox in children.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Lillies one pint, Fat four oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Oyl of Roſes one ounce, waſh them a good-while with the water of Roſes and Lil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies, then take four whites of Eggs, prepare them in their ſhells, and coagulare them a little by the fire, then mix them in a morter with the former, then add of ſweet and bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Almonds blanched, each one ounce, then beat and incorporate them with the former, and adde the roots of Reeds two drams and a half; Sarcocol, Melon-ſeeds cleanſed, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:119632:61"/>of Gold, Sugar, Marrow, Aniſe, Chalk, each one dram, mix them all in a morter to the form of a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments for Scabs.</head>
                  <p>Take of live Sulphur half a pound, as much Salt, Hogs-greaſe two pound, Oyl of Bays half a pint, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another more powerful for the Scab and ſalt Fleag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge, yellow Arſnick, Quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſilver, Tartar, Maſtick, Olibanum, live Sul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phur, each half an ounce, old Hogs-greaſe ſix ounces, Oyl of Bays two ounce, a little Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another free from all danger.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine waſht in Roſe-water, three drams, Oyl of Roſes four ounces, Juice of Orenges, a ſufficient quantity, three yelks of Eggs, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh Butter ſix drams, Jaſmine, Alume, common Salt, each two drams, the Juice of ſowre Dock, of Fumitory, each half an ounce, three yelks of Eggs, powder of Orrice two drams, liquid Styrax ſix drams, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:119632:62"/>
                  <head>Another approved one againſt any Scab, Ringworm, or Tetter.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge, Alume, Quickſilver, each half a dram, Roſes, Ceruſſe, Savine, the fiſh Sepia, Cadmian earth, each one dram; the aſhes of Maſtick-tree, Calamint, each half a dram, mix them with Juice of Mint, and boyl them with Oyl of Roſes to a third part, adding a little Wax.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Scabs in children.</head>
                  <p>Take of waſht Turpentine, one ounce, the yelk of an Egg, Oyl of Flax, one ounce and a half, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of waſht Butter two ounces, waſht Turpentine three ounces, Salt, yelks of Eggs, Oyl of Roſes, each one ounce, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of freſh Butter waſht with Fumito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-water, waſht Turpentine, common Salt, each three ounces, two yelks of Eggs, Juice of orenges as much as is ſufficient, mix them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ointments that beautifie the face.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Face bright.</head>
                  <p>TAke Oyl of Tartar three ounces, ſeeds of Fleawort one ounce, infuſe them in
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:119632:62"/>the mucilage, mix and diſſolve with them in an ounce of Oyl of Roſes, Borax, ſalt Gem, each one dram, and make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Colouring for the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Citrine Ointment freſh made three ounces, ſweet Almonds very well brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, flour of Beans, each one dram, the bone of the fiſh Sepia, Harts-horn, Barley flour, each two drams, incorporate them all with Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sea-frogs without their ſhell, put them in a glaſs veſſel, and ſprinkle them with the pouder of ſalt Gem, and cover them with Lemmon-water, and ſet them ſo long in the ſun till they become like an Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with which anoint the face, afterwards waſh it with Bean-flower water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Citrine Ointment four ounces, Pomatum two ounces, mix and anoint night and morn, then waſh with Bean-flower wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Liniment after the manner of Virgins milk, to adorn the Face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge of Gold two ounces, boyl it in a little leaden veſſel, with ſix oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of white wine vineger diſtilled, ſtirring
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:119632:63"/>it all the while with a ſtick, ſtrein it through a linnen cloth, and keep the water; at laſt take of Salt, or Oyl, or Tartar, one ounce, and diſſolve it in a glaſs with four ounces of Water of Lillies, then take in your hand three or four drops of each of the afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid waters, and they will turn to a Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins milk, with which rub the face, and let it dry in.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to illuſtrate the face.</head>
                  <p>Take the Oyl of the Marrow of a Hart, two ounces, Oyl of Goard-ſeeds one ounce, Goats far, waſht Turpentine, each half an ounce, new Wax three drams, melt them by the fire, then adde Maſtick, Borax burnt, each two drams, mix them and make an Unguent, with which anoint the face at night, and in the morning waſh it with Bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To whiten the face.</head>
                  <p>Take of Virgins milk two ounces, Oyl of Tartar one ounce, mix them and anoint the face at night going to ſleep, in the morning waſh it, and it will be clear, bright and fair.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Of Ointments to whiten the hands.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſalt Lard bruiſed and ſteeped in a Lye three days, (changing the Lye twice a
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:119632:63"/>day) a ſufficient quantity, white Wax a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, white Lilly-roots roaſted under the aſhes and bruiſed, two; melt them by the fire, then paſs it through a thin ſearſe, into cold water, waſh it well, changing the water five or ſix times, afterwards keep it in a glaſs veſſel for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Goats far or ſuer cleanſed, and ſteep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in Roſe-water two dayes, and very well waſht, a ſufficient quantity, bruiſe it in a morter, continually waſhing it with Roſe-water, then add white Wax, Musk, Sivet, each as much as ſufficient melt them together, and diffuſe it in Roſe-water, or ſome other ſweet water, then keep it for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of bitter Almonds well waſht in Roſe- or Violet-water, a ſufficient quantity, white Wax enough, mix them by the fire, and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Melon and Goard-ſeeds cleanſed, Pine-nuts cleanſed, Peach-kernels, Barley<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flour, each one part, bruiſe them all well, then with one pint of Honey, mix them to the form of an Unguent, with which anoint the hands at night, and waſh in the morn.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:119632:64"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of ſweet Almonds well waſht, white Wax, each a ſufficient quantity, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure one dram, mix them and make an Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the root of white Orrice one ounce, Lilly-roots three ounces, white Sugar one ounce, bruiſe them all well, and make them up to the form of a paſte, with which rub the hands, then waſh them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Tartar, Oyl of ſweet Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds, white Wax, each a ſufficient quanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, diſſolve them by the fire, and adde Myrrhe pouder'd, one dram, Maſtick brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed two drams, mix and infuſe them in Roſe-water, waſh them, and then adde Musk, Ambergreece, Camphure, each a little, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of Goards, Melons husked, Pine-nuts cleanſed, Peach-Kernels, each ſix ounces, Barley-bran a ſufficient quantity, pouder them and mix them with the beſt Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pine-nuts cleanſed and bruiſed,
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:119632:64"/>one pound, Muſtard-ſeed one ounce, Fige three ounces, Camphure two drams, beat them all well and mix them, and make a paſte to rub the hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to make the hands fair.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Oyl waſht, freſh Butter waſht, Goats fat waſht, each one part, ſteep them together four and twenty houres in Roſe-water, then diſſolve them by the fire, and adde white Wax a ſufficient quantity, a little Musk, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the crum of Bread, Rice, red Vet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, each three ounces or four, ſoft Soap an ounce and a half, ſcum'd Honey a ſufficient quantity, make a paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Juice of Pompions a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, bitter Almonds infuſed in Whey, as much as is ſufficient, a hundred Figs infu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in the ſame, Muſtard-ſeed two ounces, Orrice-roots one ounce, Ox Gaul five drams, incorporate them and make a paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take a pint of water in an earthen veſſel, leaded and well covered, and boyl half away, then adde Juice of Lemmons ſix ounces, Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney,
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:119632:65"/>Oyl of bitter Almonds, each two oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for hands ſwelled with cold.</head>
                  <p>Take the greaſe of Wooll, Gooſe, and Ducks greaſe, the mucilage of Quince-ſeeds, each two ounces, Starch-corn ſix drams, Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentine one ounce and a half, Oyl of Roſes, Oyl of yelks of Eggs, each two ounces, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Wax a little, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to waſh the hands.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pine-nuts cleanſed, powder of Muſtard-ſeed, each three ounces, the beſt Honey half a pint, mix them and make a paſte.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for hands ſwelled with cold.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of Flax, Fenigreek, Marſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mallows, each half a dram, of Mucilage ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracted of Lilly-water, and the fore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned ointment, each one ounce, oyl of Dill, oyl of ſweet Almonds, each half an ounce, make a Liniment for the hands with courſe Wooll.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For Clefts of the hands.</head>
                  <p>Take ointment of Litharge, of Ceruſſe, each one dram, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rams-greaſe, Starch-corn, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tharge,
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:119632:65"/>Oyl, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Litharge of Silver, Myrrhe, Gin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, each a like parts; Honey, Wax, Oyl, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for clefts of the Hands and cold.</head>
                  <p>Take of common Oyl four ounces, white Frankincenſe, clean Wax, each one ounce, the Juice of Elder-leaves three ounces, well ſcented white wine four ounces, boyl an Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the Wine, Oyl and Juice of Elder, afterwards adde the Frankincenſe and Wax, and then ſtrein it.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Anoint them with the roots of ſoure Dock and Sows-greaſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the clefts of the hands.</head>
                  <p>Take of Maſtick, Oyl of Roſes, white Wax, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bran burnt to aſhes, the hairs of a Horſe tail burnt, each one part, Honey as much as is ſufficient, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tutty, Ceruſſe, Litharge, each half a dram, Arſnick, Sublimate three granes,
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:119632:66"/>Lead, Alume, each half a ſcruple, Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Roſes, Plantane, Purſlane, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, the white of one Egg, make a mixture.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tragacanth one ſcruple, flour of Starch-corn half an ounce, Juice of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane two drams, with Syrup of Roſes make a mixture.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for ſcabby and leprous Nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rams fat, Colophony, each two drams, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Cerot for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Turpentine, Cummin, each one dram, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Maſtick, unripe Olives, each two ounces, Cynamon one dram, Ceruſſe waſht, burnt Lead, each half a dram, Tutty prepared ſix drams, white Wax, Rozen waſht with wine, each one ounce, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for a contuſion of the nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of new Wax, Cummin, Coſtmary, each a ſufficient quantity, pouder them and mix them up with the Wax.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ducks-greaſe, Bears fat, Euphor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:119632:66"/>pouder'd, each a ſufficient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Clefts of the nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of Diachylon, Oyl of Almonds, Oyl of Been, Maſtick, Raiſons, each a ſufficient quantity, make a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Flax-ſeed, Honey, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, mix them to the form of a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For leprous Nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pitch and Wax, each a ſufficient quantity, melt them together, and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Goats Suet, Sandarach pouder'd, each a ſufficient quantity.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>For pill'd Nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of Salt, Flour of Barley, Coſtmary powder'd, each one part, Honey a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment after ſhedding of the nails.</head>
                  <p>Take of Flax-ſeed one ounce, Cardamoms three drams, Honey a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to make the nails fall.</head>
                  <p>Take ointment of Roſes, Cantharides, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="116" facs="tcp:119632:67"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Miſſletoe of the oak, Arſnick, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for warts in the Hands.</head>
                  <p>Take the roots of a Vine, ſheeps-dung, and Goats-dung, each one part, the milk of Figs or of Spurge, as much as is ſufficient, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the Lees of Oyl, Sugar-alume, each one ounce, Verdegreaſe two ounces, Tar half an ounce, mix them and uſe them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take ruſt of Braſs, yellow Arſnick, Dates, unſlaked Lime, froth of the Sea, Tartar, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triol, Pigeons-dung, the floure of Rie, of Gith, each equal parts, Bulls-gaul, as much as is ſufficient, make an Unguent to lay on the Warts firſt ſcarified.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>The bark of Sallow burnt, and mixt with Vinegar, and laid on; alſo a Dogs-turd with Wax.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Ointments that adorn the Breſt.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To keep the Breaſts ſmall.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Roch-alume pouder'd a ſufficient quantity, Oyl of Roſes as much as is
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:119632:67"/>ſufficient, mix them and anoint the breaſt.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bolearmenick pouder'd, green Gauls bruiſed, each one part, Honey a ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient quantity, make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ceruſſe, white Marble, each one part, Oyl of Myrtels a ſufficient quantity, pouder them and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Breſts decreaſe or grow leſs.</head>
                  <p>The juice of Hemlock mixt with Camp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hure and layd on, makes them leſs; alſo white Frankincenſe with Navel-wort and ſharp Vinegar, hinders their growth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment to hinder their growth.</head>
                  <p>Take a ſufficient quantity of Dyers-earth, boyl it with Honey, and make a thick Poul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſſe, and apply it from morning to night, then lay over it a Spunge ſoaked in cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter till the Poulteſſe be taken off, and if you would have it more effectual, mix with it ten unripe Gauls, it will make them right and ſtreight.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To harden ſoft and looſe Breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Take clay, the white of an Egge, unripe, Gauls, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, bruiſe them all and mix them with hot Vinegar, and anoint the breaſt,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:119632:68"/>and ſuffer it to lye on all night; if once will not do, do it again.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To hinder the growth of the Breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Bruiſe Hemlock, and let a Maſs of it with Vineger be laid on a Virgins breaſt, it will ſo confine them that they grow not, though at the time of milk coming in them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Liniment to ſmooth flaggy, wrinckled Breaſts.</head>
                  <p>Take Lees of Oyl, as much as is ſufficient, Gum-arabick, Tragacanth, Maſtick, each a little, Camphure a very little, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Breaſts leſs and hard.</head>
                  <p>Take of green Mint, dryed Roſes, wilde Pears, Medlars, Servaces, Slooes, Juice of binding Bean-tree, Pomegranate-flowers, Pomegranate-rinde, unripe Pine-nuts, Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane, Flowers of Archangel, each alike parts, bruiſe them and boyl them in Vineger, then adde flour of Beans, as much as is ſufficient, make a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Quinces, unripe Plums, each a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, bruiſe them very well, and adde Bolearmenick, Plantane-ſeed, Aniſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed, Fennel, Cummin, each a little, Juice
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:119632:68"/>of Plantane, Vineger, each a ſufficient quan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Breaſts that hang down.</head>
                  <p>Take of Bean-flower, Frankincenſe, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, Juice of Houſleek, hot Vineger, whites of Eggs, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of dried Figs, Raiſons, Cummin, Vineger, each as much as is ſufficient, bruiſe them and boyl them to the form of a Plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Gauls, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, whites of Eggs, hot Vineger, each as much as will ſuffice, mix them: Bran boyled with Vineger and laid on the Breaſts, will do the like.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for Clefts of the Nibbles.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes, the middle rinde of Elder, each one ounce, Wax as much as is ſufficient, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for pain proceeding of Clefts.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Violets, or Oyl of ſweet Almonds, white Frankincenſe, Wax, each
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:119632:69"/>two drams, and then mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another for Clefts.</head>
                  <p>Take Badgers fat half an ounce, Martia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum, and <hi>Agrippa's</hi> Ointment, Ointment of Marſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mallowes, and that called <hi>Anodyne,</hi> each one dram, Oyl of Nard one ounce and a half, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Roſes two ounces, new Wax half an ounce, Litharge, Frankincenſe, each one dram, mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Tragacanth one ſcruple, flour of Starch-corn two ounces, Juice of Plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tane three drams, mix them and anoint.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Ointments to adorn the Belly and Feet.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To take away the Wrinckles of the Belly after Childe bearing.</head>
                  <p>TAke of burnt Harts-horn, the ſtone <hi>Amiantus,</hi> Ammoniack, Salt, Myrrhe, Frankincenſe, M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtick, each as much as is ſufficient, pouder and mix them with Honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="121" facs="tcp:119632:69"/>
                  <head>Another of the ſame.</head>
                  <p>Take of Rams Suet, nine times waſht in cold water, one pound, two whites of Egges, a little Butter, bruiſe them all very well, then adde Maſtick, Olibanum, each two drams, mix them and make an Ointment for the Belly.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Sea-onion burnt, burnt Harts-horn, Plumed-Alume, Ammoniack. Salt, Myrrhe, Olibanum, Maſtick, Gith, Barley-flour, each a like parts, pouder and mix them with honey.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An Ointment for hardneſs of the feet.</head>
                  <p>Take the flour of Gith, the flour of old Bread-corn, Wax, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them, and make a Cerot to lay on the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Drink made with Vineger and Honey, Ammoniacum, each one ounce Bdel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium, Sagapen, each two drams, Turpentine three drams, Oyl of Orrice, two ounces, mix them and make an Unguent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the aſhes of the rinde of Sallow, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neger, each as much as will ſuffice, mix them and anoint the place.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="122" facs="tcp:119632:70"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the green leaves of Rue, Raifons, each a ſufficient quantity, bruiſe them toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and make a Plaiſter.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Galbanum, Wax, each a ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent quantity, and mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A brave-ſcented Ointment.</head>
                  <p>Take of Musk, Ambergreece, Sivet, each four granes, with Oyl of ſweet Almonds, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duce them to the form of an Ointment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Or thus:</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Nutmegs made by a Preſs, one dram, the beſt Sivet one ſcruple, choice Musk ſix granes, Oyl of Spike, Lavender, each two or three drops, mix them and make an Ointment to anoint the Noſtrils, Fore-head, and principal parts, to fortifie them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Soaps that Beautifie.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A white Sweet-ſmelling Soap.</head>
                  <p>TAke of old Venetian Soap ſcraped, and ſix days ſet in the ſun, as much as is ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:119632:70"/>beat it very well with one pint of the beſt Roſe-water, then diſſolve it by a gentle fire, and adde powder of Orrice four ounces, Starch-corn ſix ounces, white Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders two ounces, liquid Styrax, Oyl of Spike, each one ounce, mix them very well, and when it is cold, make balls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A muskified Soap.</head>
                  <p>Take of the beſt Soap ſcraped one pound, choice Cynamon, Nutmeg, Cane, Styrax, each one ounce, wood of Aloes two drams, Benjamin two ounces, Cloves one ounce, beat them all to a fine powder, and adde powder of Cy<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>erus one dram, Musk, Siver, each a little, dip them in Roſe-water, after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſet them in the ſun for forty days, and make Balls, which muſt be kept in Cotton in woodden veſſels.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A white ſweet Soap.</head>
                  <p>Take of old common Soap ſcraped, a ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient quantity, dry it well for eight dayes or ten, then bruiſe it and ſearſe it, and adde Powder of Orrice four ounces, white Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders three ounces, Mahaleb two ounces, flour of Starch-corn one omnce, powder them all and mix them, and put them in a
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:119632:71"/>morter together, with one ounce of liquid Styrax, and a little Oyl of Spike, beat them all well together, and at laſt with the Flour of Starch-corn; make Balls, dry them in the ſhade, and keep them for your uſe.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another moſt excellent one.</head>
                  <p>Take ſix granes of Musk diſſolved in Roſe-water, Sivet four granes, mix them with the fore-mentioned Soap, but the Musk muſt be hot in the Roſe-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another to whiten the hands.</head>
                  <p>Take of bitter Almonds cleanſed and brui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed one pound, Turky-ſoap the bigneſs of an Egg, Muſtard-ſeed one ſpoonful, pouder them all and mix them.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Powders to adorn the Teeth.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Powder to make them white.</head>
                  <p>TAke of red Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>al. Date-ſtone Pummy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone, the bones of the fiſh Sepia, burnt Salt, each a ſufficient quantity, mix them and make a Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="125" facs="tcp:119632:71"/>
                  <head>Another to faſten the Teeth, and ſtrengthen the Gums.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Corral, Pearl, Dragons blood, Bolearmenick, Frankincenſe, Crabs ſhells, each one part, mix them and make a Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An excellent Dentifrice.</head>
                  <p>Take of Hyſſope, Organy, Mint, each two ounces, cleft Alume, Harts-horn, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Salt, each one dram, take them and burn them in a pot to coales, then adde Pepper, Pummy-ſtone, Pellitory of Spain, Maſtick, each half a dram, Myrrhe, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, each one ſcruple, make a fine Powder.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Powder to whiten the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Take the bones of the fiſh Sepia, white Marble burnt, each one ounce, Cloves, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, Pellitory of Spain, each three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Spunge, Pummy-ſtone, Salt, each one ounce, mix them and make a fine Powder to rub the Teeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Ginger, Cynamon, Cloves, Pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>myſtone, wood of Aloes, Nutmeg, Mace, each
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:119632:72"/>half an ounce, Pepper, Pellitory of Spain, Muſtard-ſeed, Staveſacer, each three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Spunge, white Marble, each half an ounce, Date-ſtones burnt white Hellebore, each two ounces, Barley bread burnt with Salt and Honey, half an ounce; red Tyles, burnt Harts-horn, Feather'd-alume, Olive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones burnt, Myrobalane-ſtones burnt, each three ounces, mix them and make a fine Powder.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Powders to adorn the Hands,</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>To make the Hands white.</head>
                  <p>TAke the flour of Beans, of Lupines, of Starch-corn, Rice, ſmall Beanes, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, each ſix ounces, mix them and make a Powder, with which waſh the hands in water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Pine-nuts cleanſed and bruiſed two ounces, Muſtard-ſeed one pound, Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monds cleanſed and bruiſed two ounces; make a Powder and dry it in the ſun, with which rub the hands with the Juice of Lem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, and then with water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="127" facs="tcp:119632:72"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take the ſeeds of Rocket ſix ounces, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice, Cummin, each one ounce, dregs of Alume half an ounce, Sugar-candy, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacanth, each one ounce, Camphure one ſcruple, Pine-nuts, Almonds cleanſed three ounces, the crum of white bread half an ounce, old Soap ſcraped two ounces, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them all and mix them, and make a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to waſh the hands.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Dentifrice to whiten the Teeth.</head>
                  <p>Take of Roſemary, Mint, Pennyroyal, each half a dram, Orrice-roots, Cammels<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hay, each one ſcruple; Nard, Pepper, each half a ſcruple, Pummy-ſtone, burnt Salt, Harts-horn, each two ſcruples, make them up with Tragacanth ſteeped in Roſe-water. Sticks of the Maſtick-tree may be found fit to cleanſe and ſtrengthen the teeth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Corral one ounce, Majori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>can earth half an ounce, the bones of the fiſh Sepia, Pummy-ſtone, each two drams; Cloves, Cynamon, Maſtick, each one ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, choice Pearl one dram, Dragons blood two drams, Musk one grane, pouder them
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:119632:73"/>and work them into a maſs with Tragacanth ſteeped in Roſe-water; of which make Den<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifrices like penſils.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Harts-horn, a Horſes teeth, each two ounces, Sea-ſhells, common Salt, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs nuts, each one ounce, burn them to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in an Oven, and make a Powder, to be wrought up with the mucilage of Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragacanth.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another in Powder.</head>
                  <p>Take of Myrrhe, Maſtick, Frankincenſe, each half an ounce, Harts-horn burnt and waſht, red Corral, Roſes, Musky-Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Cloves, each two ſcruples, the bone of the fiſh Sepia, Roche-alume burnt, each two drams, Pummy-ſtone one dram and a half, common Salt burnt one dram, make a Powder; you may uſe it with a Mallow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>root prepared.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another eminent one.</head>
                  <p>Take the tops of Myrtle, of Maſtick-tree, Wilde-Olive, Sage, Roſemary, each one handful; red Corral, Ivory, Horſes-teeth, each half an ounce, common Salt
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:119632:73"/>one pugil, burn them together in an earthen veſſel till they be white, then pouder them and adde of Cloves, Roſes, thick Cynamon, each three ounces, mix them and rub the Teeth, or with the Cremor of Tragacanth make long Penſils.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of Perfumes.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A ſweet Bag.</head>
                  <p>TAke of Cubebs half a dram, Cloves one ſcruple, Gith burnt one ounce and a half, Mace two ſcruples, pouder them and put them into ſilk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Violet Powder.</head>
                  <p>Take Orrice of Florence half a pound, Roſes four ounces. Cyperus half an ounce, Marjoram, Cloves, each half a dram; ſweet-ſcented white Saunders, Benjamin, each four ounces, Styrax-calamite one ounce, pouder them and put them in ſilk for a ſcent.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Florentine Flower-de-luce four pound, dried Marjoram one fourth, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lamus-Aromaticus three ounces, Roſes,
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:119632:74"/>Violets, each five drams; Cloves half an ounce, Musk one dram, pouder them and put them in ſilk.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Orrice of Florence two pound, red Roſes one pound, Styrax-calamite, Cloves, white Saunders, Aromatick, Cane, Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riander, Cyperus, each four ounces; Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joram, Lavender, each ſix drams; Sivet, Musk, each a ſufficient quantity, then mix them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Pomander.</head>
                  <p>Take of Styrax-calamita one ounce, Cloves two drams, Benjamin half an ounce, Ambergreece half a dram, Musk fifteen granes, of the aforeſaid Violet-powder a ſufficient quantity, Roſe-water as much as will make it up.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Styrax-calamita one ounce and a half, Benjamin two ounces, Labdanum half an ounce, Cloves, white Saunders, each three drams; Roſes, Marjoram, each two drams and a half; Musk, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, each one ſcruple; make a Pomander
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:119632:74"/>with the infuſion of Gum-tragacanth in Roſe-water.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Styrax-calamite, liquid Styrax, Benjamin, Gallia Moſchata, Alipta Moſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chata, Labdanum, each one ounce, choice Cynamon, Cloves, white Saunders, each half an ounce, red Roſes, Nutmeg, Mace, Wood of Aloes, Cardamoms, Marjoram, Gum-Elemni, Gith-ſeed, Zedoary, each a dram and a half, Turpentine as much as is ſufficient, with a little infuſion of Traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canth made in Roſe-water, then make a maſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of yellow Saunders ſix drams two ſcruples, Wood of Aloes half an ounce, red Roſes, Baſilicon, Lavender, Roſema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry-flowers, Marjoram, each three drams one ſcruple, Citron-pill ſeven drams; Cyna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, Nutmeg, Mace, Cloves, Coriander<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeed prepared, Cardamoms, each three drams one ſcruple; pure Labdanum eight ounces, Styrax-calamita ſix drams two ſcru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, liquid Styrax three ounces, Benjamin ten drams, yellow Wax one ounce and a
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:119632:75"/>half, Turpentine four ounces, Roſe-water two ounces and a half, Musk of Alexandria, Ambergreece, each two ſcruples and a half, make a maſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Powder of Violets a dram and a half, Roſes, Marjoram, Styrax-calamite, Labda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num, each one dram, Cloves two drams, Benjamin, Nutmegs, each one ſcruple; Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bergreece half a ſcruple, make a maſs with Roſe-water, in which Tragacanth and Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arabick have been ſteeped, and ſprinkle it with a little Oyl, either of Cynamon, or Cloves, or Nutmegs.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Styrax three drams, Cloves, Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>namon, each two drams, Mace, Nutmeg, each one dram, Wood of Aloes half a dram, Musk, Ambergreece, each three granes, Maſtick one dram and a half, pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and ſearſe them, then make them up with the diſtilled Water of Marjoram, and liquid Styrax, and make round ſweet Balls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="133" facs="tcp:119632:75"/>
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Virgins Wax four ounces, Oyl of Olives, Turpentine, each half an ounce, Labdanum three drams, Olibanum, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtick, each a dram and a half, Myrrhe, Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax-calamite, each two drams, white and red Been, red Roſes, dried Mint, Marjo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, Cloves, Cardamoms, white and red Saunders, Cynamon, Nutmeg, Wood of Aloes, Camphure, each one dram, Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece, Musk, each half a dram, pouder them and make a Pomander.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Pomander for the time of Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum, Styrax-calamite, each one dram, Cloves half a dram, Camphure, Nard, Nutmeg, each ſeven granes, bruiſe them all to a fine pouder, and mix them with Roſe-water in which Tragacanth and Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>arabick have been ſteeped, and make Balls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum three ounces, Sty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rax-calamite one ounce, Benjamin half an ounce, Cloves three drams, red Roſes two drams, Wood of Aloes, white Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, each one dram, Majoram, Lavender, Gith-ſeeds, each half a dram, Camphure three granes, liquid Styrax half an ounce,
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:119632:76"/>with the infuſion of Gum-tragacanth in Roſe-water make a Pomander, the rich may adde a little Musk and Ambergreece.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Pomander that will purge.</head>
                  <p>Take of Scammony, Aloes, Myrrhe, each one dram, Spurge, Coloquintida, each one dram and a half, powder and ſearſe them, and with the Juice of Coriander make two Pomanders; which hold in your hands, often changing them from one hand into the other, that they may be hot and alter the air.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another againſt the Plague.</head>
                  <p>Take the Flowers of Water-lillies, Bug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loſs, Violers, Roſes, each one dram, Pome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citron rinde one dram and a half, Mace half a dram, all the Saunders, each a dram and a half, white Poppy one ſcruple, Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phure half a ſcruple, Labdanum two drams, Ambe regreece four granes, powder them and make them up with the diſtilled Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Lettice and liquid Styrax, and make ſweet Balls.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take of Styrax-calamita, Benjamin,
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:119632:76"/>eace one ounce, Labdanum, Maſtick, each half an ounce, Cloves, Wood of Aloes, yel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Saunders, each one dram; Gith-ſeeds two drams, with a little Venice-Turpentine, make ſweet balls, and aromatize them with a little Musk, and Amber-greece diſſolved in Oyl of Cloves.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A ſweet Ointment.</head>
                  <p>Take of Musk, Ambergreece, Sivet, each four granes, Oyl of ſweet Almonds, as much as is ſufficient, make a Liniment.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Another.</head>
                  <p>Take Oyl of Nurmeg made by a preſs, one dram, the beſt Sivet one ſcruple, choice Musk ſix granes, Oyl of Spike, Oyl of Laven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, each two drops or three, make an Ointment, to anoint the forehead, noſtrils, and other principal parts.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Candle for a Perfume.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſweet Aſa, Styrax-calamita, each four ounces, red Styrax, Olibanum, each twelve ounces, Labdanum eighteen ounces, Cloves one ounce and a half, Gith one ounce, Coriander prepared, Juniper-berries, each half an ounce, liquid Styrax ſix-ounces,
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:119632:77"/>Turpentine half an ounce, Coales of Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree or Sallow, thirty ounces, with the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion of Gum-tragacanth made in Roſe-water, make Candles.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Perfuming Candles againſt Poyſon and Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum three ounce, Styrax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>calamita ten drams, ſweet Aſa ſix drams, Frankincenſe one ounce and a half, French Lavender two ounces, red Roſes, Cloves, each three ounces, Pomecitron-pills, yellow Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, each two drams, Juniper-berries half an ounce, Amber-greece, Musk, each half a ſcruple, Coals of Line-tree one pound and a half, mix them all with Gum-tragacanth and Roſe-water warm, and bring them into a Maſſe, then make ſmall Candles out of it, and dry them gently.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Muskified Soap.</head>
                  <p>Take of Venetian Soap four pound, cut it very ſmall, and add pouder of Cloves, white Saunders, each two ounces, Benjamin one ounce, Musk twenty granes, temper them with Roſe-water, ſome add a few drops of Oyl of Spike, but Oyl of Cloves or Mace will do better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="137" facs="tcp:119632:77"/>
                  <head>Balls againſt the Plague or Peſtilence.</head>
                  <p>Take of Labdanum three drams, powder of Roſes, Aromatick-cane, Orrice, the true Dittander, Angelica, Cynamon, ſweet Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Nutmegs, each two ſcruples, Benjamin, two drams and a half, Amber-greece one ſcruple, Musk twenty granes, Styrax-cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mita, half an ounce, with ſix ounces of Gum-Arabick or Tragacanth, infuſed in one ounce of Roſe-water, make Balls according to Art, and anoint them with Oyl of Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Of ſweet Scents or Perfumes.</head>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Troches for Perfumes.</head>
                  <p>TAke Wood of Aloes, Labdanum, Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jamin, each two drams, Styrax-cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mite half a dram, Sugar-candy three oun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, Musk two granes, mix them with Roſe-water into a Paiſte, and make Troches, which will ſmell the better if you ſprinkle a little Roſe-water on them when you uſe them.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <pb n="138" facs="tcp:119632:78"/>
                  <head>Troches of Gallia Moſchata.</head>
                  <p>Take raw Wood of Aloes, choice and good, five parts, Ambergreece three parts, good Musk one part, Mucilage of Traga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>canth diſſolved in Roſe-water, as much as will ſuffice to make them up, and make Troches of the figure of a Myrtle-leaf, ſeal them up, and put them in an Earthen Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>Troches of Benjamin.</head>
                  <p>Take of Benjamin ſix ounces, Wood of Aloes eight ounces, Styrax-calamite three ounces, Musk half a dram, Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice two ounces, Sugar-candy three pound, powder them, and with Roſe-water make Troches.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>The Counteſs of <hi>Arnsburg's</hi> Perfume.</head>
                  <p>Take freſh white Roſes bruiſed four ounces, Benjamin ſteeped in Roſe-water a day and a night, two ounces; Amber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greece three granes, Musk two granes, Siver one grane, powder and beat them with the Roſes, then adde of the beſt Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gar
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:119632:78"/>half an ounce, then let them alone in a morter, well covered for two dayes, then work them into a maſs, and make Troches; but you muſt mix a little Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tragacanth ſteeped in Roſe-water, and Gum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dragon to make them ſtick together the better.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>A Perfume made in the form of little Birds.</head>
                  <p>Take of red Styrax half a pound, liquid Styrax one ounce, Styrax-calamite one ounce and a half, coals of Sallow, Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gacanth, each two drams; let the powder of the Coals and the Tragacanth be ſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped three days in Roſe-water, then work them into a maſs, of which make the figures of Birds.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="remedy">
                  <head>An excellent Perfume for Candles or Troches.</head>
                  <p>Take of ſweet Aſa half an ounce, Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of Orrice two drams, Wood of Aloes, Nutmeg, Cloves, Maſtick, each one dram, Styrax-calamite two drams, all the Saun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, each half a ſcruple, Camphure five
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:119632:79"/>granes, Ambergreece, Musk, each four granes, white Sugar four ounces, with the mucilage of Tragacanth and a little liquid Styrax and Roſe-water with Musk, make Candles or Troches.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:119632:79"/>
            <head>The Contents of the Book.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>IT teacheth to make variety of ſweet Waters, for the Body or Garments, to illuſtrate and adorn the face, to take away Freckles, Skars, Sun-burns, Pimples, Redneſs; with the Art of making ſeveral Colourings or Fucuſſes, alſo how to take away Spots, Bunchings, Warts; to kill Ring worms, to ſmooth Wrinkles, raze out the marks of the ſmall Pox; with Potions to make the Body fat or lean, ſweet Baths to cleanſe the body, alſo how to colour the Hair of any colour whatſoever, to make it grow thick, to make it curl, to lengthen it, to cauſe it to grow where it is wanting, and take it away where it is ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluous, to hinder the ſhedding of it; alſo to cure all blemiſhes or infirmities of the eyes and teeth, with Dentrifrices and Powders to cleanſe and whiten them: to make Lotions, Lyes, and Oint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments; As alſo to cure ſore Heads, Dander, Nits, Lice, Scabs, Scars, Leproſies, Tetters, Scalds and Burns; to whiten the hands, to take away all deformities of womens breaſts: how to make ſweet and muskified Soaps to waſh with; alſo Perfumes, ſweet Bags, Pomanders for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light, and thoſe that will purge by ſmelling to them, Candles that perfume as they burn, and ſeveral Troches for Perfumes.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
